<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Go in peace. Containing some brief directions for young ministers, in their visitation of the sick Useful for the people, in their state both of health, and sickness.</title>
            <author>Martin, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834029</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834029</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38508</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38508)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1836:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Go in peace. Containing some brief directions for young ministers, in their visitation of the sick Useful for the people, in their state both of health, and sickness.</title>
                  <author>Martin, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 163, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A. M. for Richard Royston, bookseller to his most sacred Majesty, a the Angel in Amen-Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Martin by Wing.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Training of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:1"/>
            <p>Go in Peace.</p>
            <p>Containing ſome Brief DIRECTIONS For Young MINISTERS, In their Viſitation of the Sick.</p>
            <p>USEFUL For the People, in their ſtate both of Health, and Sickneſs.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 32.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O that they were wiſe, that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood this, that they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their latter end!</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, at the Angel in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sr. <hi>George How,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Author prayeth the increaſe of Grace here, and Glory hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is receiv'd for a truth of the <hi>greater magnitude,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12.19.</note> by One, whoſe <hi>Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> renders his conceptions unſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of any <hi>bias</hi> by <hi>interest;</hi> That the <hi>Goſpel</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>Miniſters</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ever weighed in the ſame <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> of human <hi>judgment;</hi> and the <hi>eſtimate</hi> of both, whether of <hi>honour,</hi> or <hi>contempt,</hi> always <hi>alike.</hi> The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere eſteem you have for the <hi>Duties</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> doth not only mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the <hi>certainty</hi> of that <hi>Maxim;</hi> but alſo lay open the <hi>Root,</hi> out of
<pb facs="tcp:38508:3"/>which, your <hi>pious</hi> regard for the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> thereof, doth <hi>grow</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</hi> Both which, daily <hi>thriving</hi> by the Celeſtial <hi>ſhowers</hi> of <hi>Divine Grace</hi> falling on your heart, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo <hi>conſpicuous</hi> in the World, <hi>(like a City ſet on an hill, that cannot be hid)</hi> that it hath engag'd my weak endeavours to contribute ſomething to the <hi>preſent imitation,</hi> and <hi>future memory</hi> of your Vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I am confident (whatever <hi>others</hi> may do, yet) you will not eſteem your ſelf unconcern'd, in the <hi>purpoſe,</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> of this <hi>Collection:</hi> For who can do ſo, that believes, <hi>That it is appointed to men once to dye, and after that, the Judgment?</hi> Much leſs then, a Perſon, <hi>who dyes daily:</hi> whoſe <hi>contemplation</hi> minutely ſuggeſt unto him the <hi>memento's</hi> of mortality; and whoſe <hi>life</hi> is an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire deſign</hi> to prepare for death. Did other foreſee what kind of thoughts would ſuprize them at that <hi>woful day,</hi> (unleſs their ſpirits are <hi>congeal'd</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38508:3"/>by ſome <hi>narcotick</hi> ſtupidity) they would deem it as much beneath the <hi>ſagacity</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> as the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to leave the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant buſineſs of their <hi>life,</hi> to be <hi>hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled</hi> up in a few <hi>tempeſtuous</hi> hours, encumbred with <hi>ſorrow, pain, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, horrour</hi> and <hi>amazement</hi> in themſelves, and others. And who is there that can <hi>make</hi> a <hi>death-bed</hi> ſo well, that an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcerous</hi> Soul may <hi>lye</hi> eaſie on it, under the <hi>throws</hi> and <hi>pangs</hi> of a <hi>wounded</hi> Conſcience? It is to this (almoſt) <hi>inſuperable</hi> task, that I have adventured to ſet an <hi>help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand;</hi> (rather indeed endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to prevent the <hi>huge</hi> difficulty of that <hi>work</hi>) to bring out of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre</hi> of a <hi>crucified Jeſus</hi> a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Relique,</hi> as I may ſay; ſome part of the <hi>Napkin,</hi> that was <hi>bound about his head</hi> (as an <hi>Handkerchief,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pron</hi> from the <hi>body of an Apoſtle</hi>) wherewith to <hi>ſtanch</hi> the <hi>blood; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite,</hi> and <hi>avert</hi> the <hi>death</hi> of a <hi>ſinner;</hi> yea, bring to him <hi>pardon, life,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:38508:4"/>
               <hi>immortality,</hi> inſtead of it. And who is he, that dares reject a <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi> (how <hi>deſperate</hi> ſoever be the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Patient</hi>) the <hi>ingredients</hi> whereof are gathered out of the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> of God; the <hi>Book of Scriptures?</hi> Who ſhall limit that <hi>mercy, that is above all his works;</hi> the <hi>ſupreme</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Divine Omnipotency?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> though I do not altogether deſpair of the proſperous ſucceſs of this <hi>charitable enterprize</hi> on <hi>others;</hi> yet thus much I can ſafely promiſe my ſelf (which will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompence the little trouble I ſhall give them) that it will free my <hi>Brethren</hi> from all <hi>umbrage</hi> of <hi>ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> to ſo <hi>ſincere</hi> a <hi>Lover</hi> of the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy:</hi> and put the World in mind; how <hi>great</hi> a <hi>price</hi> is to be ſet on <hi>Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> when <hi>ſet-out,</hi> and <hi>imbelliſh't</hi> with <hi>Greatneſs: This</hi> being the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs,</hi> whereby the <hi>inferior world</hi> of men do <hi>ſteer</hi> their <hi>courſe</hi> and is the <hi>Anchor</hi> of <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> under all the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Viciſſitudes</hi> of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:4"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>THere are ſome, I preſume, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Reverend <hi>Clergy</hi> of that <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> of which I profeſs my ſelf an unworthy <hi>member,</hi> who need not be put in mind of a <hi>paſſage,</hi> touching the <hi>Concerns</hi> of their <hi>Function,</hi> that fell from the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> lips of a late <hi>godly Prelate</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> in his <hi>Speech</hi> at his <hi>Primary</hi> (and <hi>last</hi>) <hi>Viſitation;</hi> in which he preſt them to a <hi>zealous, diſcreet,</hi> and <hi>ſedulous</hi> performance of their duty of <hi>Preaching.</hi> For which, amongſt other, he gave theſe <hi>two</hi> important Reaſons. The <hi>one,</hi> from an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation himſelf had made, whilſt he liv'd in <hi>Exile,</hi> (for he was one of thoſe <hi>Abiathar's,</hi> 1 King. 2.26. <hi>that
<pb facs="tcp:38508:5"/>was afflicted in all wherein his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty was afflicted</hi>) of the <hi>groſs</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> ignorance of the <hi>common People,</hi> in thoſe <hi>parts</hi> beyond the Seas, where himſelf converſt: which he imputed chiefly to the want of <hi>frequent Sermons</hi> amongſt them. And his <hi>other</hi> was taken from the <hi>ſtate</hi> of things in this <hi>Church;</hi> which though, by its <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Rubricks,</hi> it exacts from <hi>Ministers</hi> ſincere, and diligent <hi>Preaching</hi> to the <hi>People;</hi> yet hath it not laid any <hi>coercive</hi> obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the <hi>People</hi> themſelves, to have <hi>private</hi> recourſe to their <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the <hi>latter</hi> of theſe Reaſons that I principally reflect on, as a very importunate motive to all <hi>zealous,</hi> and <hi>pious Miniſters</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> to lay hold on every precious opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity they can, for <hi>private</hi> Diſcourſe with them, whoſe <hi>ſouls</hi> are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their <hi>charge;</hi> thereby to faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate a way to their <hi>own</hi> comfort, and the ſalvation of their <hi>Brethren.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38508:5"/>Both which are ſo nearly concern'd in their <hi>Viſitation of the ſick; (that One later</hi> than the <hi>Eleventh hour,</hi> for that ſort of <hi>addreſs</hi>) that I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the boldneſs to <hi>put them in mind of their duty,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. <hi>though they know it already,</hi> by delivering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hand, ſundry <hi>pertinent,</hi> and <hi>uſeful</hi> paſſages of <hi>Scripture,</hi> proper to ſupply the <hi>unskilfulneſs</hi> of ſuch, as are but <hi>newly</hi> entered on that <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Function.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>moment</hi> of which duty let me recommend to them in the words of <hi>Salvian,</hi> an <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Church. It is,</hi> ſays he,<note place="margin">Revocare ab inquiſitione ultimi Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dii, durum ac impium eſt. Spondere au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aliquid in tam ſera curatione, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarium. Sed melius eſt ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil inexpertum relinquere, quam morientem non curare. Maxime quia neſcio an in extremis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid tentare medicina ſit, certe nihil tentare, perditio. <hi>Salv. ad Eccl. Cathol. l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>an harſh and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious thing, to diſcourage any one, from ſlying to the last Remedy: And no leſs raſh is it, to promiſe any thing, in ſo late an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the ſpiritual cure.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:38508:6"/>
               <hi>Yet better is it, to leave nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tried, then not to have regard to a departing Soul. Eſpecially, ſeeing I know not, whether to attempt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, may not prove ſucceſsful; but it would certainly prove deſtructive, to make trial of no remedy at all. But a greater than</hi> Salvian <hi>is here:</hi> When I ſay unto the wicked, thou ſhalt ſurely dye, and thou giveſt him not warning, nor ſpeakeſt to warn the wicked from his wicked way to ſave his life; the ſame wicked man ſhall dye in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at thy hand. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.19.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:6"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> DIrections when a ſick Perſon ſeems wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of his ſpiritual ſtate. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> When he expreſſes ſome penitence for his ſins. <hi>p. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> When he is under too great deſpondency <hi>p. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> When under ſuſpicion of ungrounded confidence. <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Rules for the Trial of his State. <hi>p. 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> When the occaſion or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of his ſickneſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him. <hi>p. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> When oppreſſed with fears of dying. <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Application to ſeveral
<pb facs="tcp:38508:7"/>cauſes that may make a perſon unwilling to dye. <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> When the ſick perſon ſeems willing to dye. <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> When he complains of the want of ſenſible joy. <hi>p. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> When he doubts of the truth or ſeaſonableneſs of his Repentance. <hi>p. 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Directions how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean ones ſelf in ſickneſs. <hi>p. 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Exerciſe of Prayer in time of ſickneſs. <hi>p. 135.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> A Prayer to be uſed in a ſtate of Health. <hi>p. 145.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> A Prayer when one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himſelf to be ſick. <hi>p. 148.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Prayers to be uſed in a Family. <hi>p. 152.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38508:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>GO in PEACE.</hi> Containing ſome brief Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for Young Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is to deal with a <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> he muſt prudently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, of what <hi>Quality</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> the Perſon is, as well in <hi>natural,</hi> as <hi>civil</hi> (or <hi>moral</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; his <hi>Age, Sex, Education, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Offices, Profeſſion, Poverty, Wealth,</hi> and the like. All know that there are <hi>peccata diverſorum ſtatuum,</hi> as the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> ſpeak, ſins to which one <hi>State</hi> (or <hi>ſort</hi>) of men is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious, and not another; and ſome, more than others; to which, good
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38508:8"/>heed muſt be taken. We muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member St. <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> method, in giving to every one his <hi>due portion;</hi> of whom the <hi>Father</hi> ſays; that <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis generationibus hominum conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens Baptiſta tribuit reſponſum;</hi> the anſwer the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> gave to all that ask'd him, was ſuch as was ſuitable to every ones <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> How the <hi>Sick Perſon,</hi> in the <hi>Miniſters</hi> own knowledg, or in the eſteem of <hi>good men,</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean'd himſelf, in the common du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety; Tit.</hi> 2.12. the <hi>indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Rules of every ones converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What is the preſent frame, and temper of his mind? Whether <hi>inſenſible</hi> of the <hi>guilt,</hi> and <hi>pollution</hi> of his ſins; or <hi>perplext,</hi> and <hi>troubled above meaſure;</hi> or elſe in a <hi>middle,</hi> and <hi>ſeeming</hi> poſture of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and quiet: And <hi>laſtly,</hi> what his preſent indiſpoſition by ſickneſs will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38508:8"/>not permit him to bear; that the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> opperſs him, not with <hi>unneſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Diſcourſes,</hi> and <hi>Preſcriptions,</hi> much leſs with ſuch as are <hi>imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> appear <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible</hi> of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> dangers, the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> muſt prudently conſider; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>inſenſibleneſs</hi> doth ariſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from</p>
            <p n="1">1. A ſtupid ignorance of ſuch things, a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ought to know and believe to his Souls health; or from</p>
            <p n="2">2. A preſumptuous boldneſs, and regardleſneſs of his ſpiritual ſtate; not caring how it may go with his Soul in the other World: Or from</p>
            <p n="3">3. An ill-plac't confidence, and conceit of his own performances of ſome Acts of <hi>common Juſtice, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> or other <hi>moral</hi> Vertue; whereby many are deluded, <hi>thinking themſelves to be ſomething when they are nothing,</hi> being in truth void of all <hi>ſaving</hi> Faith, and other <hi>Spiritual</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38508:9"/>Graces. Or from</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reſting on external conformity, to the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Worſhip, Order,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church, of which he is a <hi>member,</hi> and the profeſſion of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> it Teacheth, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſcionable obedience of Gods Laws. Or from</p>
            <p n="5">5. That common Errour, namely, that <hi>true juſtifying</hi> Faith conſiſts <hi>in believing one ſhall be ſav'd;</hi> and ſo, all further enquiry into his ſtate deemed impertinent, and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Or from</p>
            <p n="6">6. Preſent Diſtemper of ſickneſs, depriving him, in ſome meaſure, of an ability to underſtand, and reflect on the things that concern his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al welfare: which many times hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to them, whom we ought to eſteem good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the ſight and ſenſe of his Sins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt with the ſame prudence and caution conſider,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38508:9"/>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the Sins, he complains of, be the <hi>whole,</hi> or no more but a <hi>partial</hi> cauſe of his troubles; or, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, rather an <hi>effect,</hi> than a <hi>cauſe</hi> it ſelf; as it commonly <hi>happens</hi> upon <hi>diſcontents,</hi> ariſing from things of this World. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether his ſickneſs be not of that kind, that may diſpoſe him to <hi>ſadneſs</hi> of Spirit, and <hi>Melancholick</hi> perturbations of mind: Which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more ſurely diſcovered, than by conſidering the nature of thoſe ſins, of which he complains. Which if no other but <hi>common frailties,</hi> they ſeem to point out ſome unuſual <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of heart, or <hi>distemper</hi> of judgment, ariſing either from <hi>natural constitution</hi> of body, <hi>reflection</hi> on former lapſes, preſent <hi>infirmity,</hi> or the <hi>ſuggestion</hi> of Satan: In which Caſe, without <hi>ſincere</hi> confeſſion, there is no relief, or comfort to be given him; but by <hi>accident,</hi> a <hi>cure</hi> may be <hi>hit</hi> on; <hi>adviſed</hi> it cannot be.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38508:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> ſeem to be in a <hi>Christian</hi> temper, and frame of mind, in reſpect of his <hi>faith, hope,</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> yet is there a <hi>portion</hi> to be adminiſtred to him in this ſeaſon: Either</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Admonition,</hi> to ſearch, and aſſure himſelf, of a <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>ſolid</hi> ground of his <hi>hope;</hi> that that <hi>Anchor</hi> of his Soul deceive him not, in his greateſt need. Or</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of <hi>Encouragement,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to enlarge the comfort, and <hi>rest</hi> of his Soul by fit <hi>Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and conſtant <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>vigilancy</hi> over his heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> A Like Duty is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on the <hi>Minister</hi> in ſome other <hi>reſpects;</hi> as when the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth great <hi>willingneſs,</hi> or <hi>unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs</hi> to dye; <hi>ſolicitude</hi> for Wife, and Children, <hi>payment</hi> of Debts, and the like. For all which, and ſuch like <hi>emergencies,</hi> it is neceſſary, that the <hi>ſpiritual Phyſician</hi> be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't with ſuitable <hi>paſſages,</hi> and <hi>Texts</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38508:10"/>of Scripture; as being that which is moſt powerful in <hi>converting the Soul, strengthning</hi> and <hi>refreſhing</hi> the Spirit, and <hi>ſupporting</hi> it againſt all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: And hath alſo a <hi>ſpecial property</hi> in <hi>ſearching</hi> out, and <hi>aſcertaining</hi> the heart: And we may aſſure our ſelves, that there is no ſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men in this Life, for which there is not in the <hi>Book of God</hi> a <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be found, which its the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> duty to give him in that <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore that the <hi>Man of God</hi> may be readily <hi>ſurniſh'd for that work,</hi> with <hi>choice</hi> of <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> and <hi>powerful remedies</hi> for the more <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> diſeaſes of his <hi>Flock,</hi> theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>directions</hi> may, by Gods bleſſing, become ſucceſsful; when <hi>diſcreetly</hi> and <hi>diligently</hi> applyed to the ſeveral exigents of our <hi>Brethren:</hi> Upon any of which the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may enlarge himſelf, as he ſees cauſe, in the <hi>opening</hi> and <hi>applying</hi> the ſame, on <hi>particular</hi> occaſions.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38508:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First</hi> then, When the <hi>Sick Perſon</hi> appears wholly <hi>inſenſible</hi> of his <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> ſtate, (the common danger of <hi>Christians,</hi> who either feel not, or pretend they feel not any <hi>gripes,</hi> or <hi>mindings</hi> of their Conſciences,) ſuch paſſages of Scripture are fitteſt, that may ſet before him;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Majesty and Greatneſs of God;</hi> as <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.16. And it came to paſs on the third day in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there were Thunderings and Lightnings, and a thick Cloud upon the Mount, and the voice of the Trumpet exceeding loud; ſo that all the people, that was in the Camp, trembled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. And Mount Sinai was altogether on a ſmoak, becauſe the Lord deſcended upon it in fire: And the ſmoak thereof aſcended as the ſmoak of a furnace, and the whole Mount quaked greatly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chapt</hi> 20.18. And all the People ſaw the Thunderings and the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and the noiſe of the Trumpet,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38508:11"/>and the Mountain ſmoaking: And when the peope ſaw it, they remov'd and ſtood afar off. And ſo terrible was the ſight, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly fear and quake. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.20. Thou <hi>[Moſes]</hi> canſt not ſee my face, for there ſhall no Man ſee me, and live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 21. Behold there is a place by me, and thou ſhalt ſtand upon a Rock.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. And it ſhall come to paſs whil'ſt my glory paſſeth by, that I will put thee in a clift of the Rock, and will cover thee with my hand, whil'ſt I paſs by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23. And I will take away mine hand, and thou ſhalt ſee my back parts, but my face ſhall not be ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.22. It is he that ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the circle of the Earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are as Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: That ſtretcheth out the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens as a Curtain, and ſpreadeth them out, as a Tent, to dwell in.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38508:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23. That bringeth the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to nothing; and maketh the Judges of the Earth as vanity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.—Let us have grace, whereby we may ſerve God accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, with reverence and godly ear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29. For our God is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The Divine Attributes; eſpecially of his.</hi> 1. <hi>Holineſs,</hi> 2. <hi>Justice.</hi> 3. <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holineſs, Gen.</hi> 28.16, 17. And Jacob awaked out of his ſleep, and he ſaid, ſurely the Lord is in this place, and I knew it not. And he was afraid, and ſaid, how dreadful is this place? This is none other but the Houſe of God, and this is the Gate of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5. Draw not nigh hither: put off thy Shoes from off thy feet, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt is holy ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 19.12.—Take heed to your ſolves, that ye go not up into the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38508:12"/>Mount, or touch the border of it: Whoſoever toucheth the Mount ſhall be ſurely put to death.</p>
            <p n="13">13. There ſhall not a hand touch it, but he ſhall ſurely be ſtoned, or ſhot through; whether it be beaſt or man, it ſhall not live.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.19. And he [the Lord] ſmote the men of Bethſhemeſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had looked into the Ark of the Lord, even he ſmote of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Fifty thouſand and threeſcore and ten men. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. And the men of Bethſhemeſh ſaid, Who is able to ſtand before this holy Lord God?</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. Uzzah put forth his hand to the Ark of God, and took hold of it, for the Oxen ſhook it. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. And God ſmote him there for his errour, and there he dyed by the Ark of God. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. And David was afraid of the Lord that day, and ſaid, how ſhall the Ark of the Lord come to me?</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. As he, who hath call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you is Holy, ſo be ye Holy in all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38508:13"/>manner of converſation. 16. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is written, be ye holy, for I am holy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. Follow peace with all men, and holineſs; without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Justice. Gen.</hi> 18.25.—Shall not the Judg of all the Earth do right?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.—I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, viſiting the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me: <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. And ſhewing mercy unto thouſands of them that love me, and keep my Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.15. Righteouſneſs and equity are the habitation of thy ſeat. And 119.137. Righteous art thou, O Lord, and true are thy judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2. We are ſure, that the judgment of God is according to truth, againſt them which commit ſuch things. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. Who will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to every man according to his deeds, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. To them, who by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38508:13"/>patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for glory, and honour, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, eternal life. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. But unto them, that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; indignation, and wrath, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. Tribulation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil: <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. But glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and peace, to every man, that worketh good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. Behold, I come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and my reward is with me, to give every man according as his work ſhall be.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Power. Gen.</hi> 18.14. Is any thing too hard for the Lord?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.22. Fear ye not me, ſaith the Lord, will ye not tremble at my preſence; which have placed the ſand for a bound of the ſea, by a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual decree, that it cannot paſs, and though the waves thereof toſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet can they not prevail, though they roar, yet can they not paſs over it? And <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.7. Who
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38508:14"/>would not fear thee, O King of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? For to thee doth it appertain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.20. Bleſſed be the Name of God for ever and ever? for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and might are his. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. He changeth the times and the ſeaſons; he removeth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.4. Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and gloriſie thy Name? for thou only art holy; for all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall come and worſhip before thee, for thy judgments are made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acknowledged and fear'd by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Religion themſelves;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.27. The Lord is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and I and my people are wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.29. Then Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar ſpake and ſaid; Bleſſed be the God of Shadrach, Meſhach, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednego; who hath ſent his Angel, and delivered his Servants that truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in him, and have chang'd the Kings word, and yielded their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38508:14"/>that they might not ſerve, nor worſhip any God, except their own God. <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. Therefore I make a Decree, that every People, Nation, and Language which ſpeak any thing amiſs againſt the God of Shadrach, Meſhach, and Abednego, ſhall be cut in pieces, and their houſes ſhall be made a dunghil, becauſe there is no other God, that can deliver after this ſort. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.25. Then Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us wrote unto all People, Nations, and Languages that dwelt in all the earth: <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. I make a decree, that in every Dominion of my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, men tremble and fear, before the God of Daniel: for he is the living God and ſtedfaſt for ever, and his Kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed, and his Dominion ſhall be even unto the end. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27. He delivereth, and reſcueth, and he worketh ſigns and wonders in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and in Earth: Who hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Daniel from the Power of the Lions.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:38508:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. And as Paul reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come, Felix trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15. And the Kings of the Earth, and the great men, and the Rich men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty men, and every bondman, and every freeman, hid themſelves in the Dens, and in the Rocks of the Mountains. <hi>Verſe</hi> 16. And ſaid to the Mountains and Rocks; fall on us, and hide us from the face of him, that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb. <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. For the great day of his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The State of an Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In reſpect of original corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Job.</hi> 14.4. Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean? Not one. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.14. What is man that he ſhould be clean? and he that is born of a Woman, that he ſhould be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38508:15"/>righteous? <hi>Verſe</hi> 15. The Heavens are not clean in his ſight; <hi>verſe</hi> 16. How much more abominable, and filthy is Man, that drinketh iniquity like water? <hi>Chap.</hi> 25.4. How then can Man be juſtified with God? Or how can he be clean, that is born of a Woman?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. Behold, I was ſhapen in wickedneſs, and in ſin hath my Mother conceived me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 3.5. Except a Man be born of Water and of the Spirit, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdom of God. <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. That which is born of the Fleſh, is Fleſh; and that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. — By the offence of one, judgment came upon all men unto condemnation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In reſpect of actual ſin. Exod.</hi> 32.33. Whoſoever hath ſinn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, him will I blot out of my Book.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.18. Therefore the Lord was very angry with Iſrael,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38508:16"/>and removed them out of his ſight, there was none left but the Tribe of Judah only. <hi>Verſe.</hi> 19 Alſo Judah kept not the Commandments of the Lord their God, but walked in the ſtatutes of Iſrael which they made. <hi>Verſe</hi> 20. And the Lord rejected all the ſeed of Iſrael, and afflicted them, and delivered them into the hand of ſpoilers till he had caſt them out of his ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 4.8. They that plow iniquity, and ſow wickedneſs, reap the ſame. <hi>Verſe</hi> 9. By the blaſt of God they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and by the breath of his noſtrils are they conſumed. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.11. Can the Ruſh grow up without mire? can the Flag grow without water? <hi>Verſe.</hi> 12. Whilſt it is yet in its greenneſs, and not cut down, it wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth before any other herb. <hi>Verſe</hi> 13. So are the paths of all that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, and the hypocrites hope ſhall periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.24. As I live ſaith the Lord, though Coniah, the Son of Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38508:16"/>King of Judah were the ſignet upon my right hand, yet would I pluck thee thence. <hi>Verſe</hi> 25. And I will give thee into the hand of them, who ſeek thy life. <hi>Verſe</hi> 26. And I will caſt thee out, and thy Mother that bare thee, into another Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where ye were not born, and there ſhall ye dye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.26. Every one that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them not, ſhall be likened unto a fooliſh Man, which built his houſe upon the ſand. <hi>Verſe</hi> 27. And the rain deſcended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that houſe, and it fell, and great was the fall of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19. The works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe; adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, uncleanneſs, laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, idolatry, witcheraft, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murders, drunkenneſs, revellings, and ſuch like; they which do ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38508:17"/>things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. If any man worſhip the Beaſt, and his image, and receive his mark in his forehead, or in his hand; the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, into the cup of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb, and the ſmoak of their torment aſcended up for ever, and ever.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:38508:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>When the Miniſter finds not in the ſick perſon a total hardneſs and impenitency, he muſt wiſely min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Threatnings and Comforts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: To which purpoſe ſuch-like paſſages of Scripture will be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9, 10. Know therefore that the Lord thy God, he is God, the faithful God, which keepeth Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Mercy, with them that love him, and keep his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to a Thouſand generations. And repayeth them that hate him to their face, to deſtroy them: He will not be ſlack to him that hateth him, he will repay him to his face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.18, 19. Thou ſheweſt loving kindneſs unto thouſands, and recompenſeſt the iniquity of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into the boſom of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, after them; the great, the mighty God, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name. Great in Counſel, and mighty in works; for thine eyes are open upon all the ways of the ſons
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38508:18"/>of men, to give every one according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.31, 32, 33. If his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren forſake my Law, and walk not in my judgments; If they break my ſtatutes, and keep not my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; I will viſit their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence with rods, and their ſin with ſcourges. Nevertheleſs, my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from him; nor ſuffer my truth to fail.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. I have ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love. Remember therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do the firſt works, or elſe I will come againſt thee quickly, and will remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>When the Sick Perſon is fallen into the other extream, and is ſenſible of little, or no comfort, the paſſages of Scripture, relating to ſuch a condition, are thoſe which ſet forth;</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:38508:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The excellency and goodneſs of the Divine Nature. Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7. The Lord paſſed by before him, and proclaimed, The LORD, the LORD GOD, merciful and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, longſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth. Keeping mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for thouſands, forgiving iniquity and tranſgreſſion, and ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> 86.15, 16. Thou, O Lord God, art full of compaſſion, and mercy, longſuffering, plenteous in goodneſs and truth. O turn thee then unto me, and have mercy upon me: Give thy ſtrength unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and help the ſon of thine handmaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103.8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord is full of compaſſion and mercy: Longſuffering, and of great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He will not alway be chiding, neither keepeth he his anger for ever. He hath not dealt with us after our ſins; nor rewarded us according to our wickedneſs. For look how high the Heaven is in compariſon of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38508:19"/>Earth: So great is his mercy alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them that fear him. Look how wide alſo the Eaſt is from the Weſt: So far hath he ſet our ſins from us. Yea, like as a Father pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth his own Children: Even ſo is the Lord merciful unto them that fear him. For he knoweth whereof we are made; he remembreth that we are but duſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.3, 4. I taught Ephraim to go, taking them by the Arms; but they knew not that I heal'd them. I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jonah</hi> 4. Therefore I fled before unto Tarſhiſh; for I knew that thou art a gracious God, and merciful, ſlow to anger and of great kindneſs, and repenteſt thee of the evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.18, 19. Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heritage? He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth not his anger for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he delighteth in mercy. He
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38508:19"/>will turn again, he will have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon us: he will ſubdue our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and thou wilt caſt all their ſins into the depth of the Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.6. I am the Lord, I change not, therefore ye ſons of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob are not conſumed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4, 5. God, who is rich in mercy, for his great love, wherewith he loved us, even when we were dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, hath quickned us together with Chriſt (by grace ye are ſaved): And hath raiſed us up together, and made us ſit together in Heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>His incomprehenſible love, declared in giving his Son to dye for the ſin of the World</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.9, 10. Break forth into joy, ſing together ye waſt places of Jeruſalem: for the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted his People, he hath redeemed Jeruſalem. The Lord hath made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all Nations; and all the ends of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38508:20"/>earth ſhall ſee the ſalvation of our God. <hi>Chap.</hi> 53.4, 5, 6. Surely he hath born our griefs, and carried our ſorrows; yet we did eſteem him ſtricken, ſmitten of God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. But he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities: the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed. All we like ſheep have gone aſtray; we have turned every one to his own way, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all. <hi>Chap.</hi> 55.1, 3. Ho, every one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eat: yea, come buy wine and milk, without money, and without price. Incline your ear, and come unto me: hear, and your ſoul ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David. <hi>Chap.</hi> 61.1, 2, 3. The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath anointed me to preach
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38508:20"/>good tidings unto the meek; he hath ſent me to bind up the broken-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to proclaim liberty to the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the acceptable year of the Lord, and the day of vengeance of our God, to comfort all that mourn. To appoint unto them that mourn in Zion, to give unto them beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, the garment of praiſe, for the ſpirit of heavineſs, that they might be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed trees of righteouſneſs, the planting of the Lord, that he might be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.22, 23, 24, 25. I will ſave my flock, and they ſhall be no more a prey. And I will ſet up one ſhepherd over them, and he ſhall feed them, even my ſervant David; he ſhall feed them, and he ſhall be their ſhepherd. And I the Lord will be their God, and my ſervant David a Prince amongſt them, I the Lord have ſpoken it. And I will make
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38508:21"/>with them a covenant of peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malac.</hi> 4.2. Unto you that fear my Name ſhall the Son of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ariſe with healing in his wings, and ye ſhall go forth, and grow up as Calves of the ſtall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 1.76, 77, 78, 79. Thou ſhalt go before the face of the Lord to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his ways. To give knowledg of ſalvation unto his people, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins, through the tender mercy of our God, whereby the day-ſpring from on high hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited us. To give light to them that ſit in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.17, 18, 19, 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And when he [Jeſus] had opened the Book he found the place where i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was written, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon me.</hi> And he began to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto them, this day is this Scripture fulfilled in your ears.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh</hi> 1.29. John ſeeth Jeſus comin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto him, and ſaith, Behold th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lamb of God, which taketh awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38508:21"/>the ſin of the World. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.16, 17. God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son; that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.13. Greater love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his Friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Act</hi> 10.43. To him give all the Prophets witneſs, that through his Name, whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23, 24, 25. All have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, being juſtified freely by his grace, through the Redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt: whom God hath ſet forth to be a Propitiation, through faith in his blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 9. God commendeth his love towards us, in that whileſt we were yet ſinners Chriſt dyed for us. Much more then being now juſtified by his blood, we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from wrath through him.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:38508:22"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 2. If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous: And he is the propitiation for our ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. And the Elders ſung a new ſong, ſaying, Thou art worthy to take the book, and to open the ſeals thereof; for thou waſt ſlain and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood, out of every kindred, and people, and tongue, and Nation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>His faithfulneſs in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.15, 16. Can a woman for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her ſucking Child, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? yea, they may forget, yet will I not forget thee. Behold, I have graven thee on the palms of my hands, thy walls are before me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.20, 21. Thus ſaith the Lord, if you can break my covenant of the day, and my covenant of the night, and that there ſhould not be day, and night in their ſeaſon; Then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38508:22"/>may alſo my covenant be broken with David my ſervant, that he ſhould not have a ſon to reign upon his throne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28, 29. I give unto them eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any man pluck them out of my hand. My Father which gave them me is greater than all: And no man is able to pluck them out of my Fathers hand.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. God is faithful, by whom ye were called unto the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, 22. He which ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth us with you in Chriſt, and hath anointed, is God; Who hath alſo ſealed us, and given us the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the Spirit in our hearts.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. The foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this ſeal, the Lord knoweth them that are his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18. God, willing more abundantly to ſhew unto the heirs of promiſe the immutability of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, confirmed it by an Oath. That
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38508:23"/>by two immutable things, in which it was impoſſible for God to lye, we might have a ſtrong conſolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold on the hope ſet before us.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Joh</hi> 1.9. If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>His encouragements and promiſes to the penitent;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In the Law. Levit.</hi> 26.40, 41, 42. If they ſhall confeſs their iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the iniquity of their Fathers, with their treſpaſs which they treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed againſt me, and that alſo they have walked contrary to me; And that I alſo have walked contrary to them, and have brought them into the land of their enemies; if then their uncircumciſed hearts be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and they then accept of the puniſhment of their iniquity; Then will I remember my covenant with Jacob, and alſo my covenant with Iſaac, and alſo my covenant with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38508:23"/>Abraham, will I remember, and will remember the land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.27, 29, 30, 31. The Lord thy God ſhall ſcatter you among the Nations. But if from thence thou ſhalt ſeek the Lord thy God thou ſhalt find him, if thou ſeek him with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul: When thou art in Tribulation, and all theſe things are come upon thee, even in the latter days, if thou come to the Lord thy God, and ſhalt be obedient unto his voice, (for the Lord thy God is a merciful God) he will not forſake thee, neither deſtroy thee, nor forget the Covenant of thy Fathers, which he ſware unto them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 30.3. The Lord thy God will turn thy captivity, and have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon thee, and will return, and gather thee from all the Nations, whither the Lord thy God hath ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered thee. <hi>In</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Prophets.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.20, 22. Samuel ſaid unto the People, fear not, (ye have done all this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38508:24"/>wickedneſs, yet turn not aſide from following the Lord, but ſerve the Lord with all your heart) For the Lord will not forſake his people, for his great Names ſake, becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.18, 19. Though your ſins be as red as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow; though they be red as crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll. If ye be willing and obedient, ye ſhall eat the good of the land. <hi>Cha.</hi> 44.22. I have blotted out as a thick cloud, thy tranſgreſſions, and as a cloud thy ſins: return unto me for I have redeemed thee. <hi>Chap.</hi> 57.16, 17, 18. I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth: for the ſpirit ſhould fail before me, and the ſouls which I have made. For the iniquity of his covetouſneſs was I wroth, and ſmote him: I hid me, and was wroth, and he went on fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the way of his heart. I have ſeen his ways, and will heal
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38508:24"/>him, I will lead him alſo and reſtore comforts unto him, and to his mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.1, 13, 14. Thou haſt played the harlot with many lovers, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again unto me ſaith the Lord. Only acknowledg thine iniquity, that thou haſt tranſgreſt againſt the Lord thy God. Turn, O backſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing children, ſaith the Lord, for I am married unto you. <hi>Chap.</hi> 31.19, 20. Surely after that I was turned, I repented, and after that I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh; I was aſhamed, yea even conſounded, becauſe I did bear the reproach of my youth. Is Ephraim my dear Son? Is he a pleaſant child? for ſince I ſpake againſt him, I do earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him ſtill: therefore my bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els are troubled for him: I will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.8. I will cleanſe them from all their iniquity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they have ſinned againſt me; and I will pardon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l their iniquities
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38508:25"/>whereby they have ſinned, and whereby they have tranſgreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way and live: turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways, for why will ye dye, O houſe of Iſrael! <hi>In</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Goſpel. Mat.</hi> 1. 21. Thou ſhalt call his Name Jeſus, for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.11. The ſon of man is come to ſave that which was loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 15.10. There is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one ſinner that repenteth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 6.37. Him that cometh unto me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15, 16. We have not an High Prieſt which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all points tempted like as we are, yet without ſin. Let us therefore come boldly unto the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38508:25"/>Throne of grace, that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.24, 25. This man [Chriſt Jeſus] becauſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth for ever, hath an unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prieſthood. Wherefore he is alſo able to ſave them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.12. I will be merciful unto their unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>The performance of thoſe promiſes in ſeveral Inſtances of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.18. When the Lord raiſed them up Judges, then the Lord was with the Judg, and delivered them out of the hand of their enemies all the days of the Judg, for it repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord, becauſe of their groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, by reaſon of them that oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, and vexed them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.15, 16. The children of Iſrael ſaid unto the Lord, we have ſinned, do
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38508:26"/>thou unto us whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee, deliver us only we pray thee this day. And they put away the ſtrange Gods from among them, and ſerved the Lord: and his ſoul was grieved for the miſery of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.13. David ſaid unto Nathan, I have ſinned againſt the Lord. And Nathan ſaid unto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, the Lord alſo hath put away thy ſin, thou ſhalt not dye.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.29. Seeſt thou how Ahab humbleth himſelf before me? becauſe he humbleth himſelf before me, I will not bring the evil in his days: but in his ſons days will I bring the evil upon his houſe.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.12, 13. And when he [Manaſſeh] was in affliction, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord his God, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf greatly before the God of his Fathers. And prayed unto him, and he was intreated of him, and heard his ſupplication, and brought him again to Jeruſalem into his kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:38508:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.31. Nevertheleſs, for thy great mercies ſake, thou didſt not utterly conſume them, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, for thou art a gracious and merciful God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jonah</hi> 3.10. And God ſaw their works, that they turned from their evil way, and God repented of the evil, that he had ſaid, he would do unto them, and he did it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.26, 27. The ſervant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fell down, and worſhipped him ſaying, Lord have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. Then the Lord of that ſervant came moved with compaſſion, and looſed him, and forgave him the debt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 7.47. Her ſins, which are many, are forgiven, for ſhe loved much. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.42, 43. And he ſaid unto Jeſus, Lord remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom: And Jeſus ſaid unto him, verily I ſay unto thee, to day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38508:27"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15, 16. This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners of whom I am chief. Howbeit, for this cauſe I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, that in me firſt Jeſus Chriſt might ſhew forth all long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, for a pattern to them who ſhould hereafter believe on him to everlaſtinglife.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Examples of fear, and deſertion in holy men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1. And David ſaid in his heart, I ſhall now one day periſh by the hand of Saul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 7.13, 14, 15. When I ſay my bed ſhall comfort me, my couch ſhall eaſe my complaint. Then thou ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me with dreams, and terrifieſt me through viſions. So that my ſoul chooſeth ſtrangling, and death rather than my life. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.16, 17. Thou numbreſt my ſteps, doſt thou not watch over my ſins? My tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſealed up in a bag, and thou ſoweſt up mine iniquity. <hi>Chap.</hi> 30.20.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38508:27"/>I cry unto thee, and thou doſt not hear, I ſtand up, and thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeſt me not. Thou art become cruel to me; with thy ſtrong hand thou oppoſeſt thy ſelf againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.20, 21, 22. Wherefore doſt thou forget us for ever, and forſake us ſo long time? Turn thou us unto thee, O Lord, and we ſhall be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: renew our days as of old. But thou haſt utterly rejected us, thou art very wroth againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. Jeſus cried with a loud voice, ſaying, my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>When the Miniſter doth think there is cauſe to ſuſpect the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of the ſick perſon, as not ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded; for greater caution, and ſearching out the truth thereof, thoſe paſſages of Scripture are uſeful, that point at.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The deceitfulneſs of mans heart. Job.</hi> 18.5, 14. The light of the wicked ſhall be put out, and the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38508:28"/>ſpark of his fire ſhall not ſhine. His confidence ſhall be rooted out of his Tabernacle, and it ſhall bring him to the king of terrours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.21. Wo unto them that are wiſe in their own eyes, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in their own ſight. <hi>Chap.</hi> 58.2. They ſeek me daily, and delight to know my ways, as a Nation that did righteouſneſs, and forſook not the Ordinance of their God: they ask of me the Ordinances of Juſtice, and take delight in approaching unto God. <hi>Chap.</hi> 59.6. Ther webs ſhall not become garments, neither ſhall they cover themſelves with their works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9. The heart is deceitful above all things; and deſperately wicked: who can know it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 16.15. Ye are they which juſtifie your ſelves before men, but God knoweth your hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1, 2. My hearts deſire, and prayer unto God for Iſrael is, that they might be ſaved. For I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38508:28"/>bear them record, that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledg.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. Whereas there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.3, 4, 7. If a man think himſelf to be ſomething, when he is nothing, he deceiveth himſelf. But let every man prove his own work, and then ſhall he have rejoycing in himſelf alone, and not in another. Be not decieved, God is not mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James</hi> 1.26, 27. If any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you ſeem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his own heart, that mans Religion is vain. Pure Religion and undefil'd before God, and the Father, is this, To viſit the fatherleſs and widows in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the world.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:38508:29"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The ſubtilty of Satan. Gen.</hi> 3.1. The ſerpent was more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til than any beaſt of the field. And he ſaid unto the woman, ye ſhall not ſurely dye; For God doth know that in the day ye eat thereof, then your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as Gods knowing good and evil.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. And Satan ſtood up againſt Iſrael, and provoked Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid to number Iſrael.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 1.7. The Lord ſaid unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, whence comeſt thou? Then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan anſwered the Lord and ſaid; from going to and fro in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22. I will go forth, and be a lying ſpirit in the mouth of all his Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.23. Get thee behind me Satan, for thou art an offence unto me, for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but thoſe things that be of men.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:38508:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 16.16, 17. And it came to paſs, as we went to prayer, a certain damoſel poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination, met us, which brought her Maſters much gain by ſoothſaying: The ſame followed Paul, and us, and cryed ſaying Theſe men are the ſervants of the moſt high God, which ſhew unto us the way of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8, 11. I beſeech you that you would confirm your love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: Leſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us, for we are not ignorant of his devices. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.3, 14 I fear leaſt by any means, as the ſerpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty: So your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt. For Satan himſelf is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into an Angel of light.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.5. For this cauſe, when I could no longer forbear, I ſent to know your faith, leſt by ſome means the tempter have tempted you, and our labour be in vain.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38508:30"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Admonition to make a ſtrict ſearch into our hearts. Pſal.</hi> 77.6. In the night, I commune with mine own heart, and ſearch out my ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.14. They have healed the hurt of the Daughter of my People ſlightly, ſaying Peace, Peace, when there is no Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malac.</hi> 3.2, 3. Who may abide the day of his coming? and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? for he is like a Refiners fire, and like Fullers ſoap. And he ſhall ſit as a Refiner, and purifyer of ſilver.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. Every mans work ſhall be made manifeſt; For the day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by fire; and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.4. I know nothing by my ſelf, yet am I not hereby juſtified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.28. Let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread, and drink of that Cup.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38508:30"/>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Examine your ſelves whether ye be in the faith: prove your own ſelves, know you not your own ſelves that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except you be reprobates?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12, 13. The word of God is quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joints and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart. Neither is there any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſight; but all things are naked, and opened unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38508:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>James</hi> 1.25. Whoſo looketh into the perfect Law of liberty, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth therein, he being not a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1, 2. I know thy works, that thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, and art dead. Be watchful, and ſtrengthen the things that remain, that are ready to dye: for I have not found thy works perfect before God. <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. Thou ſayeſt I am rich, and encreaſed with goods, and have need of nothing: and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and poor, and blind, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Calling upon God for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. The Lord ſeeth not as man ſeeth; for man look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the outward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.23, 24. Try me, O God, and ſeek the ground of my heart: prove me, and examine my thoughts.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38508:31"/>Look well if there be any way of wickedneſs in me; and lead me in the way everlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.23. O Lord, I know that the way of man is not in himſelf: it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.10. I the Lord ſearch the heart, I try the reins; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to give every man according to his ways, and according to the fruit of his doings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James</hi> 1.5. If any of you lack wiſdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braideth not: and it ſhall be given him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The examination, and Trial of his State must be governed by ſuch rules of Scripture, as relate to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, Of his life past, with reſpect</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>To the Law of God, as it is opened and expounded by our Bleſſed Saviour in the</hi> 5th. 6th. <hi>and</hi> 7th. Chap. of St. Matthew.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:38508:32"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The duty of furniſhing his ſoul with Divine graces, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of virtue. Pſal.</hi> 45.14. The Kings daughter is all glorious within; her clothing is of wrought Gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts. For they ſhall all know me, from the leaſt of them, to the greateſt of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. I will put my ſpirit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes, and ye ſhall keep my judgments and do them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3, to 13. Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit: for theirs is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven. Bleſſed are they that mourn: for they ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. Bleſſed are the meek: for they ſhall inherit the Earth. Bleſſed are they which hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſs: for they ſhall be filled. Bleſſed are the merciful: for they ſhall obtain mercy. Bleſſed are the pure in heart: for they ſhall ſee God. Bleſſed are the peacemakers:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38508:32"/>for they ſhall be called the children of God. Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake: for theirs is the kingdom of Heaven. Bleſſed are you when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake. <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.12. Whoſoever hath, to him ſhall be giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and he ſhall have more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance: but whoſoever hath not, from him ſhall be taken away even that he hath. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.3. Verily I ſay unto you; except ye be convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, to 11. Beſides this, giving all diligence add to your faith vertue; and to vertue knowledg; And to knowledg, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, godlineſs; And to godlineſs, brotherly kindneſs; and to brotherly kindneſs, charity. For if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38508:33"/>you that ye ſhall neither be barren, nor unfruitful in the knowledg of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But he that lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe things, is blind, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old ſins. Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election ſure: for if ye do theſe things ye ſhall never fall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Performance of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duties in his ſeveral Relations, and Profeſſion. Acts</hi> 13.36. David after he had ſerved his own genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the will of God, fell on ſleep, and was laid unto his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6, 7. As we have many members in one body, and all members have not the ſame office; ſo we being many are one body in Chriſt, and every one members one of another. Having then gifts, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering according to the grace that is given to us, whether propheſie, let us propheſie according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38508:33"/>of faith. Or miniſtry, let us wait on our miniſtring. Or he that teacheth, on teaching.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1, 4, 5, 6. Children obey your Parents in the Lord. Fathers provoke not your children to wrath; but bring them up in the nurture, and admonition of the Lord. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be obedient to them that are your Maſters. Not with eye-ſervice, as menpleaſures, but as the ſervants of Chriſt. Maſters do the ſame things to them.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.1, 7. Wives, be in ſubjection unto your Husbands. Likewiſe Husbands dwell with their Wives according to knowledg, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them honour, as unto the weaker veſſel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>His preſent condition, in reference to their duties</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:38508:34"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Of Reſtitution and Satisfaction. Gen.</hi> 43.12. Take double money in your hand, and the money that was brought again in the mouth of your ſacks: peradventure it was an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.5. If a man ſhall cauſe a field, or vineyard to be eaten, and ſhall put in his beaſt, and ſhall feed in another mans field: of the beſt of his own field, and the beſt of his own vineyard ſhall he make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.18. And he that killeth a Beaſt, ſhall make it good, Beaſt for Beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11. It is not good that ye do. I likewiſe, and my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and my ſervants might exact of them money, and corn; I pray you let us leave off this uſury. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore, I pray you, to them even this day, their lands, their vineyards, their oliveyards, and their houſes, alſo the hundred part of the money, and of the corn, the wine, the oyl,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38508:34"/>that you exact of them. Then ſaid they, we will reſtore it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.8. I the Lord love judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: I hate robbery for burntoffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.1, 2. Wo unto them that deviſe iniquity: They covet fields, and take them by violence: and houſes, and take them away: So they oppreſs a man, and his houſe, even a man and his heritage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.6. Wo unto him that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth that which is not his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.1, 3, 4. I looked, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a flying Roll. This is the curſe, that goeth forth over the face of the whole earth: and it ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the houſe of the thief, and into the houſe of him, that ſweareth falſly by my Name: and it ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the middeſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it, with the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof, and the ſtones thereof.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3, 6. This is the will of God, That no man go beyond and defraud his brother in any matter,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38508:35"/>becauſe the Lord is the avenger of all ſuch.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Remiſſion of injuries ſuffered by him, and hearty reconciliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24. If thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſt that thy brother hath ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee; Leave there thy gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, and go thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.33. Shouldſt thou not alſo have had compaſſion on thy fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, even as I had pity on thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark</hi> 11. When ye ſtand praying, forgive, if ye have ought againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; that your Father alſo, which is in Heaven, may forgive you your treſpaſſes. But if you do not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, neither will your Father, which is in Heaven, forgive your treſpaſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.35. By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, that ye love one another.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38508:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. The multitude of them that believed were of one heart, and of one ſoul.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. Ye are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12, 13. Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) bowels of mercy, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, longſuffering, forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any: Even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Almesgiving, if of ability.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7, 8, 10, 11. If there be among you a poor man of one of thy Brethren, thou ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor ſhut thine hand from thy poor brother. But thou ſhalt open thy hand wide unto him, and ſhalt ſurely lend him ſufficient for his need, in that which he wanteth. Thou ſhalt ſurely give him, and thy heart ſhall not be grieved when thou giveſt unto him: becauſe that for this thing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38508:36"/>the Lord thy God ſhall bleſs thee in all thy works, and in all that thou putteſt thine hand unto. For the poor ſhall never ceaſe out of the land, therefore I command thee ſaying, thou ſhalt open thine hand wide unto thy Brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy in the land.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. Bleſſed is he that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the poor and needy, the Lord ſhall deliver him in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Lord preſerve him and keep him alive, that he may be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon earth; and deliver thou not him into the will of his enemies. The Lord comfort him when he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſick upon his bed: make thou all his bed in his ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.27. Withold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.24. There is that ſcattereth, and yet increaſeth: and there is that withholdeth more then is meet, and it tendeth to poverty.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:38508:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.1. Caſt thy bread upon the waters: for thou ſhalt find it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many days.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.37. to 41. Then ſhall the righteous anſwer him ſaying, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, and fed thee? or thirſty, and gave thee drink? When ſaw we thee a ſtranger, and took thee in? or naked, and cloathed thee? Or when ſaw we thee ſick, or in priſon, and came unto thee; And the King ſhall anſwer, and ſay unto them, verily I ſay unto you, in as much as ye have done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ye have done it unto me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 10.4. Thy prayers and thine almes are come up for a memorial be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, 18, 19. Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high-minded, nor truſt in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain riches, but in the living God, who giveth us all things richly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy. That they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38508:37"/>ſtribute, willing to communicate, Laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned Repentance for the Errours of his life paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Have mercy upon me, O God, after thy great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: according to the multitude of thy mercies, do away mine offences: Waſh me throughly from my wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs: and cleanſe me from my ſin. For I acknowledg my faults: and my ſin is ever before me. Turn thy face from my ſins: and put out all my miſdeeds. Make me a clean heart, O God: and renew a right ſpirit within me. Caſt me not away from thy preſence: and take not thy holy ſpirit from me.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>If the ſick perſon be troubled from the occaſion, or by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome circumſtances relating to his ſickneſs; the Scriptures proper
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38508:37"/>for that condition, are ſuch as ſet forth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The duty of reflecting on his former courſe of life.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.12, to the 16. And there came a writing to <hi>Jehoram</hi> from <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, ſaying, thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>David</hi> thy Father, Becauſe thou haſt not walked in the ways of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> thy Father, nor in the ways of <hi>Aſa</hi> King of <hi>Judah:</hi> But haſt walked in the ways of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and haſt made <hi>Judah</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to go a whoring, like to the whoredoms of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and alſo haſt ſlain thy brethren of thy fathers houſe, which were better than thy ſelf: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with a great plague will the Lord ſmite thy People, and thy Children, and thy Wives, and all thy Goods: And thou ſhalt have great ſickneſs by diſeaſe of thy Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, until thy Bowels fall out by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thy ſickneſs day by day. And it came to paſs, that in proceſs of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38508:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>time, after the end of two years, his bowels fell out by reaſon of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo he died of ſore diſeaſes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 26.19. And whil'ſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> was wroth with the Prieſts, the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy even roſe up in his forehead, before the Prieſts in the houſe of the Lord, from beſides the incenſe-Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.6. O remember not the ſins and offences of my youth: But according to thy mercy think thou upon me, O Lord, for thy goodneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.6. O remember not our old ſins, but have mercy upon us, and that ſoon: for we are come to great miſery. Help us, O God, of our ſalvation, for the glory of thy Name: O deliver us, and be merciful to our ſins for thy Names ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 13.26. Thou writeſt bitter things againſt me, and makeſt me to poſſeſs the iniquities of my youth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The promiſcuous diſpenſing out theſe things, both to good and bad, in this life. Gen.</hi> 35.16, 18, 19.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38508:38"/>And <hi>Rachel</hi> travelled, and ſhe had hard labour. And the midwife ſaid unto her, fear not, thou ſhalt have thy ſon alſo. And as her ſoul was in departing ſhe called his name <hi>Benoni:</hi> and <hi>Rachel</hi> died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2. And <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bihu</hi> the ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> offered ſtrange fire before the Lord, which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not. And there went out a fire from the Lord, and devoured them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12. And the Lord ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> becauſe ye believe me not, to ſanctify me in the eyes of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſhall not bring this congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the land which I have given you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judg.</hi> 20.21, 25. And the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Benjamin</hi> came forth out of <hi>Gibzah,</hi> and deſtroyed down to the ground of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that day, twenty and two thouſand men. And the ſecond day they deſtroyed down to the ground eighteen thouſand men.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38508:39"/>
            <p>I <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. And when he <hi>[the Meſſenger]</hi> made mention of the Ark of God, <hi>Eli</hi> fell from off the ſeat backward by the ſide of the Gate, and his neck brake, for he was an old man, and heavy; and he had judged <hi>Iſrael</hi> fourty years.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.29. And King <hi>Joſiah</hi> went againſt him <hi>[Pharaoh Necho]</hi> and he ſlew him at <hi>Megiddo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 2.7. Satan went forth from the preſence of the Lord, and ſmote <hi>Job</hi> with ſore biles, from the ſole of his foot, unto his crown. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.21, 22. Though I were perfect yet would I not know my ſoul: I would deſpiſe my life. This is one thing, therefore I ſaid it, he deſtroyeth the perfect and the wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.14. There be juſt men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it happeneth according to the work of the wicked: again there be wicked men unto whom it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth according to the work of the righteous. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.2. All things come alike to all; there is one event
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38508:39"/>to the righteous, and unto the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth, and to him that ſacrificeth not; as is the good, ſo is the ſinner; and he that ſweareth, as he that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an oath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.5. Like theſe good figs, ſo will I acknowledg them, that are carried away captive of <hi>Judah,</hi> whom I have ſent out of this place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the land of the <hi>Caldoeans</hi> for their good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 20.9. And there ſate in a window a certain young man named <hi>Eutychus,</hi> being fallen into a deep ſleep, and as <hi>Paul</hi> was long preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he ſunk down with ſleep, and fell down from the third loft, and was taken up dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Trophimus</hi> have I left at <hi>Miletum</hi> ſick.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Divine Clemency, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, by ſuch chastiſements, our eternal deſtruction. Joh.</hi> 5.14. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto him; Behold, thou art
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38508:40"/>made whole; ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. When we are judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we are chaſtned of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemed with the world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Diſcrimination that ſhall one day be made, betwixt ſuch as may ſuffer alike in this world. Mal.</hi> 3.14. to the end. Ye have ſaid, it is vain to ſerve God, and what profit is it, that we have kept his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and that we have walked mournfully before the Lord of Hoſts? And now we call the proud happy: yea they that work wickedneſs are ſet up: yea they that tempt God are even delivered. Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkened, and heard it, and a book of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was written before him for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name. And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day, when I make up my
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38508:40"/>Jewels, and I will ſpare them, as a man ſpareth his own ſon that ſerveth him. Then ſhall ye return, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth the Lord, and him that ſerveth him not.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The Duty of ſearching after that which doth provoke God to anger. Gen.</hi> 42.22. And they [<hi>the Brethren of</hi> Joſeph] ſaid one to another, we are verily guilty concerning our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that we ſaw the Anguiſh of his ſoul, when he beſought us, and we would not hear: therefore is this diſtreſs come upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſ.</hi> 7.13. Thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there is an accurſed thing in the middeſt of thee, O <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> thou canſt not ſtand before thine enemies, until ye take away the accurſed thing from among you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.7. And the <hi>[Mariners]</hi> ſaid every one to his fellow, come and let us caſt lots that we may know for whoſe cauſe this evil is come upon us.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:38508:41"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30, 31. For this cauſe many are weak and ſickly amongſt you, and many are fallen aſleep. For if we would judg our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20. And the reſt of the men which were not killed by theſe plagues, yet repented not of the works of their hands.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>When the ſick Perſon is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with the fear of death, ſuch Scriptures are uſeful; as ſet forth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The like fear in holy men. Pſal.</hi> 18.3, 4. The ſorrows of death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me: and the overflowings of ungodlineſs made me afraid. The pains of Hell came about me: the ſnares of death overtook me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.4, 5. My heart is diſquieted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me: and the fear of death is fallen upon me. Fearfulneſs and trembling are come upon me: and an horrible dread hath overwhelmed me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.23, 24. He brought down my ſtrength in my journey: and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38508:41"/>my days. But I ſaid, O my God take me not away in the middeſt of mine age: as for thy years they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure throughout all generations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1, 2, 3. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet the ſon of <hi>Amos</hi> came unto him <hi>[He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,]</hi> and ſaid unto him, Thus ſaith the Lord, ſet thine houſe in order: for thou ſhalt dye and not live. Then <hi>Hezekiah</hi> turned his face toward the wall, and prayed unto the Lord, And ſaid; remember now, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walkt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight: and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> wept ſore.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Comforts against fear of death, from</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The neceſſity of dying.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. Now he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt? can I bring him back again? I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not come to me. <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.14. We muſt needs dye, and are as water ſpilt on the ground, which cannot be gathered up again.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:38508:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 7.1. Is there not an appointed time to man upon earth? are not his days alſo like the days of an hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.6, 7. The voice ſaid; cry: And I ſaid what ſhall I cry? All fleſh is graſs, and all the goodlineſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is as a flower of the field. The graſs withereth, the flower fadeth, becauſe the ſpirit of the Lord blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon it; ſurely the People is graſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. It is appointed unto men once to dye.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Victory over death by Christ. Iſa.</hi> 25.8. He will ſwallow up death in victory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.14. I will ranſom them from the power of the grave: I will redeem them from death: O death I will be thy plagues, O grave I will be thy deſtruction.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25, 26. He muſt reign till he have put all enemies under his feet. The laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is death. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 54.55. When this
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38508:42"/>corruptible ſhall have put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and this mortal ſhall have put on immortality, then ſhall be brought to paſs the ſaying that is written, O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Bleſſed death of the righteous.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.28. I will gather thee to thy Fathers, and thou ſhalt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered unto thy grave in peace, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall thine eyes ſee all the evil that I will bring upon this place, and upon the inhabitants of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. Come my People, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou into thy Chambers, and ſhut thy doors about thee; hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpaſt. <hi>Chap.</hi> 57.1, 2. The righteous periſheth and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the evil to come. He ſhall enter into peace: they ſhall reſt in their beds, each one walking in his uprightneſs.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:38508:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8. Whether we live, we live unto the Lord; or whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we live therefore, or dye, we are the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, write, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works follow them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Joys to be revealed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Pſal.</hi> 16.9, 12. I have ſet God always before me: for he is on my right hand, therefore I ſhall not fall. Thou ſhalt ſhew me the path of life, in thy preſence is the fulneſs of joy, and at thy right hand there is pleaſure for evermore. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9. They ſhall be ſatisfied with the plenteouſneſs of thy houſe: and thou ſhalt give them drink of thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as out of the river. For with thee is the well of life: and in thy light ſhall we ſee light.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:38508:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.11. The redeemed of the Lord ſhall return, and come with ſinging unto <hi>Zion,</hi> and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads: they ſhall obtain gladneſs and joy, and ſorrow and mourning ſhall flee away. <hi>Chap.</hi> 64.4. Since the beginning of the World men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye ſeen, O God, beſides thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 3. At that time thy people ſhall be delivered, every one that ſhall be found written in the book. And they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the ſtars for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.23. His Lord ſaid unto him, well done, good and faithful ſervant: thou haſt been faithful over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy Lord.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:38508:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, ſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou in thy life-time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivedſt thy good things, and likewiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> evil things; but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. Father, I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory, which thou haſt given me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21, 23. To me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain. I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. After this I beheld, and lo, a great multitude, which no man could number, of all nations, and kindreds, and people, and tongues ſtood before the Throne, and before the Lamb, clothed with white robes, and palmes in their hands: And cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a loud voice, ſaying, ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our God, which ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38508:44"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The preſence of God with his hildren, in all conditions. Pſal.</hi> 41.3. The Lord comfort him when he lieth ſick upon his bed: make thou all his bed in his ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. Fear thou not, for I am with thee, be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will help thee, yea I will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs. <hi>Chap.</hi> 43.1, 2, 3. Fear not, I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine. When thou paſſeſt through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee. For I am the Lord thy God, the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience: I will alſo keep thee from the hour of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:38508:45"/>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>That ſuch ſpiritual reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may do good, the Miniſter must endeavour to underſtand and conſider from whence that unwillingneſs to die proceeds; and to the ſeveral cauſes thereof his applications of Scripture muſt be ſuitable. If</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It be from that averſation which every Creature naturally hath to diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, the beſt men have not been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together free from that fear. Joh.</hi> 21.18, 19. When thou waſt young thou girdeſt thy ſelf, and walkeſt whither thou wouldeſt: but when thou ſhalt be old, thou ſhalt ſtretch forth thy hands, and another ſhall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldeſt not. This ſpake he, ſignifying by what death he ſhould glorify God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this muſt be oppoſed,</hi> 1. <hi>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Death by Chriſt. Heb</hi> 2.14, 15. Foraſmuch as the Children are partakers of fleſh and blood: he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38508:45"/>death, that is the Devil: And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them who through fear of death were all their life-time ſubject to bondage.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56, 57. The ſting of death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law. But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 58. Therefore my beloved brethren be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as you know that your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not in vain in the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The pattern of a true Christian temper of mind.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We know, that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building with God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens. For in this we groan ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, deſiring to be clothed upon with our houſe which is from Heaven. For we that are in this Tabernacle do groan being burdened, not for that we would be unclothed, but clothed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38508:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>upon, that mortality might be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of life. Now he that hath wrought us for the ſelf-ſame thing is God, who hath alſo given unto us the earneſt of the ſpirit. Therefore we are always confident, knowing that whil'ſt we are at home in the body, we are abſent from the Lord, (For we walk by faith, not by ſight) we are confident I ſay, and willing rather to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>If from love of this World; The vanity of all earthly things, and the danger of ſuch love of the World muſt be conſidered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I made me great works, I builded me houſes, I plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me vineyards; I made me gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, and orchards, and I planted trees in them of all kind of fruits. I made me pools of water, to water therewith the wood that bringeth forth trees. I got me ſervants, and maidens, and had ſervants born in my houſe: alſo I had great poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38508:46"/>of great and ſmall cattel, above all that were in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> before me. I gathered me alſo ſilver and gold, and the peculiar treaſure of Kings, and of the Provinces: I got me men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingers, and women-ſingers, and the delights of the ſons of men, as muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal inſtruments, and that of all ſorts. And whatſoever mine eyes deſired, I kept not from them; I withheld not my heart from any joy: for my heart rejoyced in all my labours; and this was my portion of all my labour: Then I looked on all the works that my hand had wrought, and on the labour that I had laboured to do: and behold all was vanity, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit, and there was no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit under the ſun.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31. This I ſay, Brethren, the time is ſhort, It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that both they that have Wives be as though they had none: And they that weep, as though they wept not: and they that rejoyce, as though they rejoyced not: and they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38508:47"/>that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not: and they that uſe this World, as not abuſing it: for the faſhion of this World paſſeth away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.16, 17. Alas, Alas, that great City, that was clothed in fine linen, and purple, and ſcarlet, and deckt with gold, and precious ſtones, and pearls: For in one hour ſo great riches is come to naught.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The danger of it. Mat.</hi> 19.23, 24. Jeſus ſaid unto his Diſciples: verily, verily, I ſay unto you, that a rich man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. And again I ſay unto you, It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10. They that will be rich fall into temptation, and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perdition. For the love of money is the root of all evil.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:38508:47"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15, 16, 17. Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world: If any man love th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world. And the world paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof; but he that doth the will of God abideth for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 12.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Jeſus ſpake this Parable. The ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully. And he thought within himſelf, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what ſhall I do, becauſe I have no room where to beſtow my fruits? And he ſaid, this will I do, I will pull down my Barnes, and build greater, and there will I beſtow my fruits, and my goods. And I will ſay to my ſoul, ſoul thou haſt much goods layd up for many years, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry. But God ſaid unto him, Thou fool, this night thy ſoul ſhall be required
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38508:48"/>of thee: then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>If from a Conſcience burdened with the guilt of ſin, to the former Applications,</hi> p. 22, 23. <hi>may be added the tender regard of our Bleſſed Saviour, for penitent ſinners, foretold by the Prophets</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.11. He ſhall feed his flock like a ſhepherd, he ſhall gather the Lambs with his arm, and carry them in his boſom, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And proclaimed by himſelf. Mat.</hi> 11.28, 29. Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt. Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart; and and ye ſhall find reſt unto your ſouls. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30. For my yoke is eaſie, and my burden is light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.37. Jeſus ſtood and cryed ſaying, If any man thirſt, let him
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38508:48"/>come unto me and drink. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.25, 26. Jeſus ſaid [unto <hi>Martha</hi>] I am the reſurrection and the life; he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet ſhall he live: And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever liveth, and believeth in me, ſhall never dye.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>If from ſolicitude and over-great care for Wife and Children; the Scriptures pertinent, are ſuch as ſet forth</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The All-ſufficiency of God. Gen.</hi> 17.1. And when <hi>Abraham</hi> was ninety years old and nine, the Lord appeared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſaid unto him, I am the Almighty God, walk before me, and be thou perfect. And I will make my Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and thee, and will multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thee exceedingly. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.14. Is any thing too hard for the Lord? At the time appointed will I return unto thee, and <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhall have a ſon.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:38508:49"/>
            <p>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Amaziah</hi> ſaid to the man of God, but what ſhall we do for the hundred Talents, which I have given to the army of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And the man of God anſwered, the Lord is able to give thee much more than this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1. Behold, the Lord's hand is not ſhortned that it cannot ſave: neither his ear heavy that it cannot hear.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>His promiſes to his Children, and to their ſeed. Gen.</hi> 17.19. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> thy Wife ſhall bear a ſon indeed, and thou ſhalt call his name <hi>Iſaac;</hi> and I will eſtabliſh my Covenant with him, for an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and with his ſeed after him. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their generations for an everlaſting Covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.24, 25. God heard their groaning, and God remembred his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38508:49"/>Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and with <hi>Jacob.</hi> And God looked upon the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and God had reſpect unto them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſ.</hi> 21.25. There failed not ought of any good thing, which the Lord had ſpoken unto the houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> all came to paſs.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.24. Thou haſt confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thy ſelf thy People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to be a People unto thee for ever; and thou Lord art become their God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.5. He is a Father of the fatherleſs, and defendeth the cauſe of the Widows; even God in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly habitation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1, 2. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man that feareth the Lord; he hath great delight in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments. His ſeed ſhall be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon earth; the generation of the faithful ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom</hi> 8.32, 38, 39. He that ſpared not his own ſon, but delivered him up for us all; how ſhall he not with him alſo, freely give us all things? I am perſwaded that neither death,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38508:50"/>nor life, nor Angels, nor principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5, 6. Let your converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be without covetouſneſs, and be content with ſuch things as ye have; for he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee. So that we may boldly ſay, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear, what man ſhall do unto me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>His performance of them, even by the mighty working of his Power. Gen.</hi> 31.29. It is in the power of my hand to do you hurt; but the God of your Father ſpake unto me yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, ſaying, take thou heed that thou ſpeak not to <hi>Jacob</hi> either good or bad. <hi>Chap.</hi> 50.20. <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid unto them; ye thought evil againſt me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to paſs, as it is this day, to ſave much People alive.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:38508:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.12. The more they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them, the more they grew; and they were grieved becauſe of the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.3, 4, 6. Hide thy ſelf by the brook <hi>Cherith,</hi> that is before <hi>Jordan,</hi> and I have commanded the Ravens to feed thee there. And the Ravens brought him bread and fleſh in the morning, and bread and fleſh in the evening, and he drunk of the brook. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.14, 15. <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid unto her, Thus ſaith the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the barrel of meal ſhall not waſt, neither ſhall the cruſe of oyl fail, until the day that the Lord ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth rain upon the earth. And ſhe, and he, and her houſe did eat many days.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.1, to 8. Now there cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a certain woman of the wives of the ſons of the Prophets unto <hi>Eliſha;</hi> ſaying, Thy ſervant my husband is dead, and thou knoweſt that thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant did fear the Lord: And the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor is come to take unto him my
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38508:51"/>two ſons to be bondmen. And <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> ſaid unto her, what ſhall I do for thee? tell me, what haſt thou in the houſe? and ſhe ſaid, thy handmaid hath not any thing in the houſe but a pot of oyl. Then he ſaid, go bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thee veſſels abroad of all thy neighbours; even empty veſſels, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row not a few. And when thou art come in thou ſhalt ſhut the door up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and upon thy ſons, and ſhalt pour out into all thoſe veſſels, and thou ſhalt ſet aſide that which is full. So ſhe went from him, and did ſhut the door upon her, and upon her ſons; who brought the veſſels to her and ſhe poured out. And it came to paſs, when the veſſels were full, that ſhe ſaid unto her ſon, bring me yet a veſſel. And he ſaid unto her, there is not a veſſel more. And the oyl ſtaid. And ſhe came and told the man of God; and he ſaid, go ſell the oyl, and pay thy debt, and live thou and thy children of the reſt. So <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.21, 22.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:38508:51"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.5, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When Jeſus ſaw a great company come unto him, he ſaith unto <hi>Philip,</hi> whence ſhall we buy bread, that theſe may eat? <hi>Philip</hi> anſwered him. Two hundred peny-worth of bread, is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for them, that every one of them may take a little. <hi>Andrew</hi> ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, There is a lad here, that hath five barley loaves, and two ſmall fiſhes, but what are they among ſo many? Jeſus ſaid make the men ſit down. So the men ſate down in number about five thouſand. And when Jeſus had given thanks, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to the Diſciples, and the Diſciples to them that were ſet down, and likewiſe of the fiſhes, as much as they would. See <hi>Acts</hi> 5.19, 20. <hi>Ch.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.25, 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.14, to 30.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The danger of ſuch ſolicitude. Mat.</hi> 13.22. He that received ſeed among the thorns, is he that heareth the word of God, and the care of this world and the deceitfulneſs of riches
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38508:52"/>choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. God ſaid unto him, Thou fool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be required of thee: then whoſe ſhall theſe things be which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided? <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.34. Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be overcharged with ſurfetting and drunkenneſs, and cares of this life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.35. This I ſpeak for your own profit, that you may attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord without diſtraction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the unproſitableneſs of it. Pſal.</hi> 127.1, 2, 3. Except the Lord build the houſe, their labour is but loſt that build it. Except the Lord keep the city, the watchman waketh but in vain. It is but loſt labour that ye hap to riſe up early, and ſo late take reſt, and eat the bread of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.27. Which of you by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thought can add one cubit unto his ſtature?</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:38508:52"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 10.39, <hi>&amp;c. Martha</hi> had a ſiſter called <hi>Mary</hi> which alſo ſate at Jeſus feet, and heard his word: But <hi>Martha</hi> was cumbred about much ſerving, and came to him and ſaid, Lord, doſt thou not care that my ſiſter hath left me to ſerve alone? bid her therefore that ſhe help me. And Jeſus anſwered, and ſaid unto her, <hi>Martha, Martha,</hi> thou art careful and troubled about many things; But one thing is needful, and <hi>Mary</hi> hath choſen that one good part, which ſhall not be taken away from her.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Weakneſs of Faith diſcovered thereby. Mat.</hi> 6.30. If God ſo cloth the graſs of the field, which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the Oven: ſhall he not much more cloath you, O ye of little faith? <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.26. Why are ye fearful, O ye of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith? <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.31. Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Jeſus ſtretched forth his hand and caught him, and ſaid unto him, O thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:38508:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication with thankſgiving, let your requeſt be made known unto God.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. Caſting all your care up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, for he careth for you.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The duty of commanding them, we leave behind to ſerve God faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they may be bleſſed. Gen.</hi> 18.19. I know <hi>Abraham</hi> that he will command his children, and his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and judgment, that the Lord may bring upon <hi>Abraham,</hi> that which he hath ſpoken of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſ.</hi> 23.14. This day, I am going the way of all the earth, and ye know in all your hearts, and in all your ſouls, that not one thing hath failed of all the good things which the Lord your God ſpake concerning you, all are come to paſs unto you, and not one thing hath failed thereof, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24. And if it ſeem evil to you to ſerve the Lord, chuſe you this day
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38508:53"/>whom you will ſerve, but as for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.10. David bleſſed the Lord before all the congregation: and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, bleſſed be the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> our Fathers for ever and ever. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. Thine, O Lord, is the greatneſs, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, for all that is in the Heaven and the earth is thine: thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted as a head above all. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reigneſt over all, and in thine hand is power and might, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give ſtrength unto all. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. I know alſo my God, that thou trieſt the heart, and haſt pleaſure in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. O Lord God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, keep this for ever in the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the thoughts of the heart of thy People, and prepare their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38508:54"/>heart unto thee: <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. And give unto <hi>Solomon</hi> my ſon, a perfect heart to keep thy commandements, thy teſtimonies and thy ſtatutes.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I think it meet, as long as I am in this Tabernacle, to ſtir you up, by putting you in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, knowing that ſhortly I muſt put off this my Tabernacle. Moreover I will endeavour, that you may be able after my deceaſe, to have theſe things always in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>If the ſick Perſon ſeem willing to dye, the Minister may pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently endeavour to diſcover, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his willingneſs to dye doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſome good, and laudable motive, or no, for it may ariſe out of either: As</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>From a deſire to be freed from the troubles and perſecutions Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo in this life Numb.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. Whence ſhould I have fleſh to give unto all this People? for they weep
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38508:54"/>unto me ſaying, give us fleſh that we may eat. I am not able to bear all this People alone, becauſe it is too heavy for me. And if thou deal thus with me, kill me, I pray thee, out of hand, if I have found favor in thy ſight, and let me not ſee my wretchedneſs.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.4. But he <hi>[Elijah]</hi> himſelf went a days journey into the wilderneſs, and came and ſate down under a <hi>Juniper</hi>-tree, and he requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for himſelf that he might dye, and ſaid, it is enough now, O Lord, take away my life; for I am not better than my Fathers. <hi>Or</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To be freed from pain. Job.</hi> 3.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why dyed I not from the womb? why did I not give up the ghoſt, when I came out of the belly? <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. For now ſhould I have lien ſtill, and been at quiet, I ſhould have ſlept, then ſhould I have been at reſt. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17, 18. There the wicked ceaſe from troubling, there the weary be at reſt. There the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38508:55"/>reſt together; they hear not the voice of the oppreſſor. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20, 21. Wherefore is light given to him that is in miſery; and life unto the bitter in ſoul? which long for death, but it cometh not; and dig for it more than for hid treaſures? <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.8, 9. O that I might have my requeſt, and that God would grant me the thing that I long for! Even that it would pleaſe God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy me; that he would let looſe his hand, and cut me off!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.8. It came to paſs, when the ſun did riſe, that God prepared a vehement eaſtwind, and the ſun beat upon the head of <hi>Jonah,</hi> that he fainted, and wiſhed in himſelf to dye, and ſaid, it is better for me to dye, than to live. <hi>Or.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Out of ignorance of man's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate after death, in reſpect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and puniſhments. Eccl.</hi> 12.7. Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth, as it was; and the ſpirit ſhall return unto God who gave it.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:38508:55"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. It is appointed unto men once to dye, but after this the judgment.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10, 11. We muſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his body, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad. Knowing therefore the terrours of the Lord, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, 32, 33, 46. When the ſon of man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, then ſhall he be ſet upon the Throne of his glory. And before him ſhall be gathered all Nations, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from the other, as a ſhepherd divideth his ſheep from the goats. Then ſhall he ſay unto them on his right hand, come ye bleſſed Children of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the World. Then ſhall he ſay to them on his left hand; depart from me ye curſed into
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38508:56"/>everlaſting fire prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels. And theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment; but the righteous into life eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it came to paſs that the beggar dyed, and was carried by the Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom: the rich man dyed alſo, and was buried. And in Hell he lift up his eyes being in torments, and ſeeth <hi>Abraham</hi> afar off, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his boſom: And he cryed, and ſaid, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham</hi> have mercy on me, and ſend <hi>Lazarus</hi> that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame. <hi>Or</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Patient ſubmiſſion to Gods will.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. And <hi>Eli</hi> ſaid, it is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42. Father, if thou be willing remove this cup from me: nevertheleſs, not my will, but thine be done.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:38508:56"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 21.14: And when he <hi>[Paul]</hi> would not be perſwaded, we ceaſed, ſaying, the will of the Lord be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11. I have learned in what eſtate ſoever I am, therewith to be content. <hi>Or,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Well-grounded hopes of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Job</hi> 8.20. God will not caſt away a perfect man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.38. Keep innocency, and take heed to the thing that is right, for that ſhall bring a man peace at the laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. Being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. By whom alſo we have acceſs by faith into this grace wherein we ſtand, and rejoyce in hope of the glory of God.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13, 14. We having the ſame ſpirit of faith, (according as it is written, I believed, and therefore have I ſpoken: we alſo believe, and therefore ſpeak: knowing that he
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38508:57"/>which raiſed up the Lord Jeſus, ſhall raiſe up us alſo by Jeſus, and ſhall preſent us with you.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 7.8. I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith. Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord, the righteous Judg, ſhall give me at that day: and not to me only, but unto them alſo which love his appearing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.14. We are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſt, if we hold the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our confidence ſtedfaſt unto the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To each of theſe, fit applications of theſe, or ſuch-like paſſages of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are to be made. For neither wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs, nor unwillingneſs to dye ſimply conſidered, are tokens of good, or bad eſtate, but in relation t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ground, (or cauſe) from whenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they proceed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, <hi>When the ſick Perſon complains of the want of ſenſible joy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38508:57"/>and inward comfort of the Spirit, ſuch paſſages of Scripture are to be ſet before him, as deſcribe</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The state of our ſpiritual war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. Mat.</hi> 10.35, 38. I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his father, and the daughter againſt her mother, and the daughter in law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her mother in law. And a mans foes ſhall be they of his own houſhold. And he that taketh not his croſs, and followeth after me, is not worthy of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.33. In the world ye ſhall have tribulation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. The fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh; and theſe are contrary the one to the other; ſo that ye cannot do the things that ye would.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13. Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil. For we wreſtle not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fleſh and blood, but againſt Principalities, againſt powers, againſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38508:58"/>the rulers of the darkneſs of this world, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places. Wherefore take un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The complaints of holy men. Job</hi> 3.25, 26. The thing which I greatly feared is fallen upon me, and that which I was afraid of is come unto me. I was not in ſafety, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had I reſt, neither was I quiet, yet trouble came. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.4. The arrows of the Almighty are within me, the poiſon whereof drinketh up my ſpirit: the terrours of God do ſet themſelves in array againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.7, 8, 9. Will the Lord ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelf for ever, and will he be no more entreated? Is his mercy clean gone for ever: and is his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe come utterly to an end for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more?
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:38508:58"/>Hath God forgotten to be gracious: and will he ſhut up his lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs in diſpleaſure? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.6. Thine indignation lieth hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and thou haſt vexed me with thy ſtormes. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. I am in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and like unto him that is at the point to dye: even from my youth up thy terrours have I ſuffered with a troubled mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.17, 18. I ſate alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy hand: for thou haſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me with indignation. Why is my pain perpetual, and my wound incurable, which refuſeth to be heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Leſt I ſhould be exalted above meaſure through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the Revelations, there was given to me a thorn in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buſſet me, leſt I ſhould be exalted above meaſure. For this thing I beſought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me. And he ſaid unto me, my grace is ſufficient for thee: for my ſtrength
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38508:59"/>is made perfect in weakneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The return of the light of Gods countennance. Pſal.</hi> 30.5. His wrath endureth but the twinkling of an eye, in his pleaſure is life: heavineſs may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. Thou haſt turned my heavineſs into joy: thou haſt put off my ſackcloth, and girded me with gladneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71 18. O what great troubles and adverſities haſt thou ſhewed me? and yet didſt thou turn and refreſh me: yea and broughteſt me from the depth of the earth again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. I know the thoughts that I think towards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evil, to give you an expected end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Micah.</hi> 7.8. Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine enemy, when I fall, I ſhall ariſe, when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job.</hi> 14.27. Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you, not as the world giveth, give I unto
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38508:59"/>you: let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The practice of Holy men in like Caſes. Pſal.</hi> 42.6, 7. Why art thou ſo full of heavineſs, O my ſoul, and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? Put thy truſt in God, for I will yet give him thanks for the help of his countenance. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.52. I remembred thine everlaſting judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, O Lord, and received com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. Hear my Prayer, O Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts.</hi> 12.5. <hi>Peter</hi> therefore was kept in priſon, but prayer was made without ceaſing of the Church unto God for him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. Is any among you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted? let him pray.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Promiſes of deliverance. Job</hi> 5.17, 18, 19. Happy is the man whom God correcteth: therefore deſpiſe not thou the chaſtning of the Almighty. For he maketh ſore, and bindeth up; he woundeth, and his hands make whole. He ſhall deliver
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38508:60"/>thee in ſix troubles; yea in ſeven there ſhall no evil touch thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.18. Great are the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the righteous: but the Lord delivereth them out of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.11. Verily I will cauſe the enemy to treat thee well in the time of evil, and in the time of affliction. <hi>Chap.</hi> 39.16, 18. Go and ſpeak to <hi>Ebed-melech</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> ſaying, I will ſurely deliver thee, and thou ſhalt not fall by the ſword, but thy life ſhall be for a prey unto thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt put thy truſt in me, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joel</hi> 2.32. And it ſhall come to paſs, that whoſoever ſhall call on the Name of the Lord ſhall be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for in mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſhall be deliverance, as the Lord hath ſaid, and in the remnant whom the Lord ſhall call.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.14, 17. Sing, O daughter of <hi>Zion,</hi> ſhout, O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> be glad and daughter of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The Lord
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38508:60"/>thy God in the middeſt of thee is mighty: he will ſave, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over thee with joy: he will reſt in his love, he will joy over thee with ſinging. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. Behold at that time I will undo all that afflict thee: I will ſave her that halteth; and gather her that was driven out; and I will get them praiſe and fame in every land where they have been put to ſhame.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptations.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Endeavours of strengthning our Faith.</hi> I <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. And <hi>David</hi> was greatly diſtreſſed, for the people ſpake of ſtoning him, becauſe the ſoul of all the people was grieved, every man for his ſons, and for his daughters: but <hi>David</hi> encouraged himſelf in the Lord his God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.2, 3. Mine enemies are dayly in hand to ſwallow me up: for they be many that fight againſt me, O thou moſt high. Nevertheleſs,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38508:61"/>though I am ſometimes afraid, yet put I my truſt in thee. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.2, <hi>to the end.</hi> O put not your truſt in Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.5, 6. Truſt in the Lord with all thine heart, and lean not to thine own underſtanding. In all thy ways acknowledg him; and he ſhall direct thy path.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.2. Behold God is my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: I will truſt, and not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, for the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> is my ſtrength, and my ſong, he alſo is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.7. O thou that art named the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> is the ſpirit of the Lord ſtraitned? are theſe his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. The juſt ſhall live by faith. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.17, 18. Although the Fig-tree ſhall not bloſſom, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall fruit be in the vine; the labour of the Olive ſhall fail, and the field ſhall yield no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38508:61"/>and there ſhall be no herd in the ſtalls: Yet will I rejoyce in the Lord: I will joy in the God of my ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mark</hi> 5.25, 27, 28, 29. A certain woman, which had an iſſue of blood twelve years; when ſhe heard of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, came in the preſs behind, and touched his garment; For ſhe ſaid if I may but touch his clothes, I ſhall be whole. And ſtraitway the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of her blood was dryed up, and ſhe felt in her body, that ſhe was healed of that plague.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. For which cauſe I alſo ſuffer theſe things; nevertheleſs I am not aſhamed: for I know whom I have believed; and am perſwaded that he is able to keep, that which I have committed unto him againſt that day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11, 12. No chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous: Nevertheleſs after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it yieldeth the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſs, unto them which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:38508:62"/>are exerciſed thereby. Wherefore lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>When the ſick perſon doubteth of the Truth, or ſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Repentance, theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are proper, that ſet forth</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Nature of true Repentance.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him after that he had numbered the People, and <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto the Lord, I have ſinned greatly in that I have done; and now I beſeech thee, O Lord, take away the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of thy ſervant for I have done very fooliſhly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. If the wicked man will turn from all his ſins that he hath committed, and keep all my ſtatutes, and do that which is lawful and right he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye. All his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not be mentioned unto him, in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that he hath done he ſhall live.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:38508:62"/>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14. Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Fruits of it. Hoſ.</hi> 14.1, 2. O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> return unto the Lord thy God, for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquity. Take with you words, and turn to the Lord, ſay unto him, take away all iniquity, and receive us graciouſly, ſo will we offer unto thee, the calves of our lips.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 3.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O generation of Vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come? Bring forth therefore fruits worthy of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And now alſo the Axe is laid unto the root of the trees: Every tree therefore that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down and caſt into the fire. And the People asked him ſaying, what ſhall we do then? He anſwered and ſaith unto them. He that hath two coats, let him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to him that hath none: and he that hath meat, let him do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:38508:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 3.26. God having raiſed up his ſon Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. Therefore we are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him by baptiſm into death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the glory of the Father: even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.4. Wherefore, my Brethren, ye alſo are become dead to the Law by the body of Chriſt, that ye ſhould be married to another, even to him who is raiſed from the dead, that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Gods acceptance and reward of them.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.7. When the Lord ſaw they had humbled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the word of the Lord came unto <hi>Shemajah,</hi> ſaying, they have humbled themſelves, therefore I will not deſtroy them, but I will grant them ſome deliverance, and my wrath ſhall not be poured out upon <hi>Jern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Shiſhak.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:38508:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.6. I ſaid I will confeſs my ſin unto the Lord, and ſo thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaveſt the iniquity of my ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.9. If ye turn unto me, and keep my commandements, and do them; though there were of you caſt out unto the uttermoſt part of the Heaven, yet will I gather them from thence, and will bring them unto the place that I have choſen to ſet my Name there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.14, 15, 16. When I ſay unto the wicked, thou ſhalt ſurely dye, if he turn from his ſin, and do that which is lawful and right; If the wicked reſtore the pledg, give again that he had robbed, walk in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of life without committing ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye. None of his ſins that he hath committed ſhall be mentioned unto him: he hath done that which is lawful and right; he ſhall ſurely live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. The ſon of man ſhall come in the glory of his Father, with
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38508:64"/>his Angels, and then he ſhall reward every man according to his works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22. Being made free from ſin, and become ſervants to God, ye have your fruit unto holineſs, and the end everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. God is not unrighteous to forget your labour and work of love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. Their works follow them. <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.13. Death and the grave delivered up the dead which were in them, and they were judged every man according to his works.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Diligent ſearch into our ſtate, and the truth and ſincerity of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; then eſpecially, when but a ſhort time is likely to be afforded for the trial thereof.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.2. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziah</hi> did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, but not with a perfect heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 27.3, <hi>to</hi> 7. All the while my breath is in me, and the ſpirit of God is in my noſtrils; My lips ſhall not ſpeak wickedneſs, nor ſhall my
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:38508:64"/>tongue utter deceit; till I dye, I will not remove my integrity from me. My righteouſneſs I hold faſt, and will not let it go; my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.2. Examine me, O Lord, and prove me: try out my reins and my heart. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When he ſlew them, they ſought him: and turned them early, and enquired af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God. And they remembred that God was their ſtrength: and the High God was their Redeemer. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, they did but flatter him with their mouth; and diſſembled with him in their tongues. For their heart was not whole with him: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continued they ſtedfaſt in his covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.1, 2. Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet: and ſhew my people their tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> their ſins. Yet they ſeek me dayly, and delight to know my ways, as a Nation that did righteouſneſs, and forſook not
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38508:65"/>the Ordinance of their God: they ask of me the Ordinances of Juſtice, and take delight in approaching to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.3. Theſe men have ſet up their Idols in their heart, and put the ſtumbling block of their iniquity before their face: ſhould I be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of at all by them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not every one that ſaith unto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven. Many will ſay unto me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy Name? and in thy Name have caſt out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils? and in thy Name done many wonderful works? And then will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you, depart from me ye that work iniquity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. Strive to enter in at the ſtrait gate: for many I ſay unto you, will ſeek to enter in, and ſhall not be able.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:38508:65"/>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. I rejoyce, not that ye were made ſorry, but that ye ſorrowed to repentance: for ye were made ſorry after a godly manner, that ye might receive dammage by us in nothing. For godly ſorrow work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth repentance to ſalvation not to be repented of; but the ſorrow of the world worketh death. For behold, this ſelf-ſame thing that ye ſorrowed after a godly ſort, what carefulneſs it wrought in you, yea, what clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your ſelves, yea, what indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, yea, what fear, yea, what vehement deſire, yea, what zeal, yea what revenge; In all things ye have approved your ſelves to be clear in this matter.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>If the ſick perſon needs, or deſires inſtruction how to demean himſelf in his ſickneſs, ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will be uſeful, as direct us to</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Contrition for ſin. Job</hi> 42.2, 5, 6. I know that thou canſt do any thing, and that no thought can be
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38508:66"/>withheld from thee. I have heard of thee by the hearing of the ear: but now mine eye ſeeth thee. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. Who can tell how oft he offends? O cleanſe thou me from my ſecret faults. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Bleſſed is the man whoſe unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is forgiven: and whoſe ſin is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord imputeth no ſin: and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile. I will acknowledg my ſin unto thee: and mine unrighteouſnes have I not hid. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17. The Lord is nigh unto them that are of a contrite heart: and will ſave ſuch as be of an humble ſpirit. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Put me not to rebuke, O Lord, in thine anger: neither chaſten me in thy heavy diſpleaſure. For thine ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows ſtick faſt in me: and thy hand preſſeth me ſore. There is no health in my fleſh becauſe of thy diſpleaſure: neither is there any reſt in my bones
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38508:66"/>by reaſon of my ſin. For my wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes are gone over my head: and are like a ſore burden too heavy for me to bear. I truly am ſet in the plague: and my heavineſs is ever in my ſight. For I will confeſs my wickedneſs: and be ſorry for my ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.2. They conſider not in their hearts, that I remember all their wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. In many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Humility and Patience in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25, 26. And the King <hi>[David]</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Zadok,</hi> carry back the Ark of God into the City: if I ſhall find favour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſhew me both it and his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. But if he thus ſay, I have no delight in thee: behold, here am I, let him do to me, as ſeemeth good unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 2.10. What, ſhall we receive good at the hand of God, and ſhall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:38508:67"/>we not receive evil? In all this did not <hi>Job</hi> ſin with his lips. <hi>Chap.</hi> 34.31, 32. Surely it is meet to be ſaid unto God, I have born chaſtiſement, I will not offend any more. That, which I ſee not, teach thou me: If I have done iniquity, I will do no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.16. O tarry thou the Lords leaſure: be ſtrong, and he ſhall comfort thy heart, and put thou thy truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25, 26. The Lord is good unto them that wait for him, to the ſoul that ſeeketh him. It is good that a man ſhould both hope, and quietly wait for the ſalvation of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.9. I will bear the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, becauſe I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. In your patience poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs your ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.7. If ye endure chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God dealeth with you as with ſons.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:38508:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4. Count it all joy, when ye fall into divers temptations; knowing this, that the trying of your faith worketh patience; But let patience have her perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting nothing.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6. Humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reliance upon God. Deut.</hi> 33.26. There is none like unto the God of <hi>Jeſurun. Verſ.</hi> 27. The Eternal God is thy refuge. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29. Happy art thou, O <hi>Iſrael:</hi> who is like unto thee, O People, ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thy excellency?</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22. The Lord will not forſake his People, for his great Names ſake: becauſe it hath pleaſed the Lord to make you his People.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.9. The eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of them whoſe heart
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38508:68"/>is perfect towards him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 13.15. Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.13. Thou Lord wilt give thy bleſſing unto the righteous: and with thy favourable kindneſs wilt thou defend him as with a ſhield. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. They that know thy Name will put their truſt in thee: for thou Lord haſt never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them that ſeek thee. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.10. I have been left unto thee ever ſince I was born: thou art my God even from my mothers womb. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. Though I walk in the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.17. Behold, the eye of the Lord is upon them that fear him: and upon them that put their truſt in his mercy <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.40. The ſalvation of the righteous cometh of the Lord: which is alſo their ſtrength in the time of trouble. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.1. My ſoul truly waiteth ſtill upon God; for of him cometh my ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:38508:68"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.15. Thus ſaith the Lord God, the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning and reſt ſhall ye be ſaved, in quietneſs and confidence ſhall be your ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25, 26. The Lord is good unto them that wait for him, to the ſoul that ſeeketh him. It is good that a man ſhould both hope, and quietly wait for the ſalvation of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The Benefit and Comfort of Prayer. Iſa.</hi> 26.8, 9. In the way of thy judgments, O Lord, have we waited for thee: the deſire of our ſoul is to thy Name, and to the remembrance of thee. With my ſoul have I deſired thee in the night, yea, with my ſpirit within me will I ſeek thee early: for when thy judgments are in the earth; the inhabitants of the world will learn righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job.</hi> 42.10. The Lord turned the captivity of <hi>Job,</hi> when he prayed for his friends.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:38508:69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. Call upon me in the time of trouble: So will I hear thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17, 18. As for me, I will call upon God: and the Lord ſhall ſave me. In the evening and morning, and at noon day I will pray, and that inſtantly: and he ſhall hear my voice. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2, 3. Thou that heareſt prayer: unto thee ſhall all fleſh come. My miſdeeds prevail againſt me: O be thou merciful unto our ſins. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lord I make my prayer to thee, in an acceptable time. Hear me, O God, in the multitude of thy mercy: even in the truth of thy ſalvation. Take me out of the mire, that I ſink not: Oh let me be delivered from them that hate me, and out of the deep waters. Let not the deep flood drown me, neither let the deep ſwallow me up: and let not the Pit ſhut her mouth upon me. Hear me, O Lord, for thy loving kindneſs is
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:38508:69"/>comfortable: turn thee unto me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy mercies. And hide not thy face from thy ſervant, for I am in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Oh haſte thee and hear me! Draw nigh unto my ſoul, and ſave it: Oh deliver me becauſe of mine enemies. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.1, <hi>to</hi> 8. Bow down thine ear O Lord, and hear me; for I am poor, and in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Preſerve thou my ſoul, for I am holy: ſave thy ſervant, that putteth his truſt in thee. Be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to me, O Lord: for I will call dayly upon thee. Comfort the ſoul of thy ſervant: for unto thee, O Lord, do I lift up my ſoul. For thou Lord art good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious: and of great mercy unto all them that call upon thee. Give ear Lord unto my prayer: and ponder the voice of my humble deſires. In the time of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble I will call upon thee: for thou heareſt me.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:38508:70"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.13, 14. O Lord, the hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> all that forſake thee ſhall be aſhamed, and they that depart from thee ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the earth, becauſe they have forſaken the Lord, the fountain of living waters. Heal me, O Lord, and I ſhall be healed; ſave me and I ſhall be ſaved: for thou art my praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 18.1. And he ſpake a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable unto them, to this end, that men ought always to pray, and not to faint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.24. Hitherto ye have asked nothing in my Name; ask, and ye ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17. Pray without ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Meditation upon ſpiritual, and heavenly things. Deut.</hi> 22.29. O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end!</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:38508:70"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Lord, who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle? or who ſhall reſt upon thy holy Hill? Even he that leadeth an uncorrupt life; and doth the thing which is right, and ſpeaketh the truth from his heart. He that hath uſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whoſo doth theſe things ſhall never fall. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.12. So teach us to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our days; that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.4, 5. My ſpirit is vexed within me; and my heart within me is deſolate. Yet do I remember the time paſt, I muſe upon all thy works; yea, I exerciſe my ſelf in the works of thy hands.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18. For which cauſe we faint not, but though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man, is renewed day by day. For our light affliction, which is but for a moment, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory. While
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38508:71"/>we look not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4. If ye then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the right hand of God. Set your affections on things above, not on things on earth. For ye are dead, and your life is hid with Chriſt in God. When Chriſt, who is our life, ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, 12. And I ſaw a great white Throne, and him that ſate on it, from whoſe face the earth, and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them. And I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God; and the Books were opened; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book was opened, which is the Book of life: and the dead
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:38508:71"/>were judged out of thoſe things, which were written in the books, according to their works.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Choice of company fit for that time.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.14, 15. <hi>Achiſh</hi> ſaid unto his ſervants, Lo, you ſee the man is mad; wherefore then have you brought him to me? Have I need of madmen, that ye have brought this fellow to play the madman in my preſence? ſhall this fellow come into my houſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 13.4, 5. Ye are all Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of no value. O that you would altogether hold your peace, and it ſhould be your wiſdom! <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.2. Should he <hi>[a wiſe man]</hi> reaſon with unprofitable talk? or with ſpeeches where with he can do no good? <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.5. I would ſtrengthen you with my mouth, and the moving of my lips ſhould aſſwage your grief. <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.23, 24. If there be a meſſenger with him, one of a thouſand, to ſhew unto men his uprightneſs;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38508:72"/>Then he is gracious unto him, and ſaith, deliver him from going down into the pit, I have found a Ranſome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.4, 5. I have not dwelt with vain perſons, neither have I had fellowſhip with the deceitful. I have hated the Congregation of the wicked, neither will I ſit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ungodly. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mine eyes look unto ſuch as be faithful in the Land; that they may dwell with me. Whoſo leadeth a godly life, he ſhall be my ſervant. There ſhall no deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſon dwell in my houſe; he that telleth lies ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18. What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement hath the Temple of God with Idols? for ye are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Living God; as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. Wherefore come out from
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:38508:72"/>among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you. And will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſons, and my daughters, ſaith the Lord God Almighty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29. Let no corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication proceed out of your mouth, but that which is good to the uſe of edifying, that it may miniſter grace unto the hearers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14. Is any ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16. Confeſs your faults one to another, and pray one for another, that ye may be healed; the effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man, availeth much.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Hearing and Reading the Scriptures. Pſal.</hi> 119.92, 93. If my delight had not been in thy Law; I ſhould have periſhed in my trouble. I will never forget thy commandements; for with
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:38508:73"/>them haſt thou quickned me. Trouble and heavineſs have taken hold upon me; yet is my delight in thy Commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 8.28. Who <hi>[the Eunuch]</hi> returning, and ſitting in his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, read <hi>Eſaias</hi> the Prophet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. From a Child thou haſt known the Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation, through faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this Propheſie, and keep thoſe things that are written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:38508:73"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Portion of Holy Scripture that may be ſeaſonably read to the ſick, are the penitential Pſalms, (as they have been commonly called) that is to ſay, the 6th.</hi> 32, 38, 51, 102, 130, 143. <hi>The</hi> 15, 39, 90, 103. <hi>Job</hi> 14. <hi>Mit.</hi> 26, <hi>and</hi> 27. <hi>Mark</hi> 14, <hi>and</hi> 15. <hi>Luke</hi> 22, <hi>and</hi> 23. <hi>Joh. from chap.</hi> 13, <hi>to</hi> 20.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Ready and cheerful ſubmiſſion to the will and wiſdom of God. Job</hi> 1.21. And <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, Naked came I out of my Mothers womb, and naked ſhall I return thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; bleſſed be the Name of the Lord. <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.13. Why doeſt thou ſtrive againſt him? for he giveth not account of any of his matters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 39.8. Then ſaid <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Good is the word of the Lord which thou haſt ſpoken; he ſaid moreover, for there ſhall be peace and truth in my days.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:38508:74"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.6. O Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> cannot I do with you, as this Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaith the Lord? behold, as the Clay is in the Potters hand, ſo are ye in mine hand, O Houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 1.38. And <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the handmaid of the Lord, be it unto me according to thy word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20. As always, ſo now alſo Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life, or by death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2. Wherefore ſeeing we are alſo compaſſed about with ſo great a cloud of witneſſes, let us lay aſide every weight, and the ſin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us run with patience the race that is ſet before us. Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the croſs, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:38508:74"/>right hand of the Throne of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Thankfulneſs for chastiſement. Pſal.</hi> 94.12. Bleſſed is the man whom thou chaſteneſt, O Lord; and teacheſt him in thy Law. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.67. Before I was afflicted I went aſtray; but now I have kept thy word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.8. If ye be without chaſtiſement, whereof all are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, then are ye baſtards, and not ſons.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <hi>The exerciſe of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of prayer, as a ſpecial means to procure for him, what is neceſſary for his preſent condition; As</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Help againſt temptations. Pſal.</hi> 22.11, 14, 16. O go not from me, for trouble is hard at hand; and there is none to help me. I am poured out like water, and all my bones are out of joynt; my heart alſo in the middeſt of my body is even like melting wax. For many dogs are come about me; and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:38508:75"/>of the wicked layeth ſiege a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation. The ſpirit indeed is willing, but the fleſh is weak.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31, 32. Satan hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have you, that he may ſift you as wheat. But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20. Neither pray I for theſe alone; but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me through their word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.17, 18. Wherefore in all things it behoved him to be made like unto his brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful high Prieſt, in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the ſins of the People. For in that he himſelf hath ſuffered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:38508:75"/>
            <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8, 9. Be ſober, be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, becauſe your adverſary the Devil, as a roaring Lion, walketh about ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12. Wo to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth, and of the ſea; for the Devil is come down unto you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eaſe and comfort under bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pains, and anguiſh of mind. Job</hi> 7.20. I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou Preſerver of men? why haſt thou ſet me as a mark againſt thee, ſo that I am a burden to my ſelf?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.1. In thee, O Lord, have I put my truſt, let me never be put to confuſion; but rid me, and deliver me in thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, encline thine ear unto me, and ſave me. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. Be thou my ſtronghold whereunto I may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:38508:76"/>ways reſort; thou haſt promiſed to help me, for thou art my houſe of defence, and my caſtle. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. Through thee have I been holden up ever ſince. I was born; thou art he that took me out of my mothers womb, my praiſe ſhall be always of thee. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. Caſt me not away in the time of age; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me not when my ſtrength fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. Go not far from me, O God; my God, haſte thee to help me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.20. Deal thou with me, O Lord God, according to thy Name: for ſweet is thy mercy. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 21. O Deliver me, for I am helpleſs and poor: and my heart is wounded within me. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. I go hence like the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow that departeth: and an dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven away like the Graſhopper. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23. My knees are weak through faſting: my fleſh is dryed up for want of fatneſs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 1. Lord I call upon thee, haſte thee unto me: and conſider my
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:38508:76"/>voice when I cry unto thee. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. Let my prayer be ſet forth in thy ſight as the incenſe: and let the lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of my hands be an evening ſacrifice. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9. Mine eyes look unto thee, O Lord God; in thee is my truſt, O caſt not out my ſoul.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Perſeverance. Pſal.</hi> 40.14. Withdraw not thou thy mercy from me, O Lord: let thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and thy truth alway preſerve me. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. For innumerable troubles are come about me, my ſins have taken ſuch hold upon me, that I am not able to look up: yea they are more in number than the hairs of my head: and my heart hath failed me. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.14. The Lord upholdeth all ſuch as fall: and lifteth up all ſuch as be down. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. The Lord is righteous in all his ways: and holy in all his works. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18. The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him: yea, all ſuch as call upon him faithfully. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19. He will fulfil
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:38508:77"/>the deſire of them that fear him: he alſo will hear their cry and will help them. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20. The Lord preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all them that love him: but ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth abroad all the ungodly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.13. He that endureth unto the end, the ſame ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. Thou ſtandeſt by faith. Be not high-minded but fear.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. God is faithful, who will not ſuffer you to be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above that you are able; but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape that ye may be able to bear it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.3. I thank my God upon every remembrance of you. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. Always in every prayer of mine for you all, making requeſt with joy. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. For your fellowſhip in the Goſpel from the firſt day until now; <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. Being confident of this very thing, that he, which hath begun a good work in you, will perform it
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:38508:77"/>until the day of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. Even as it is meet for me to think this of you all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. Thus ſaith the Lord God, I will yet for this be inquired of by the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to do it for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A quiet departure out of this life. Gen.</hi> 49.33. When <hi>Jacob</hi> had made an end of commanding his ſons, he gathered up his feet into the bed, and yielded up the Ghoſt, and was gathered unto his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> 5.26. Thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of corn cometh in, in his ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation. <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.46. When Jeſus had cried with a loud voice, he ſaid, Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit. And having thus ſaid, he gave up the ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. They ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> calling upon God and ſaying, Lord
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:38508:78"/>Jeſus receive my ſpirit. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 60. And he kneeled down, and cried with a loud voice, Lord, lay not this ſin to their charge. And when he had ſaid this, he fell aſleep.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. He that teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, ſurely, I come quickly. <hi>Amen.</hi> Even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Minister muſt not fail to preſs the ſick perſon to receive</hi> the Holy Euchariſt; and to open to him <hi>the comfortable</hi> Doctrine, the Scripture holds forth, in <hi>that</hi> bleſſed Ordinance; this being the fitteſt cloſe <hi>for</hi> the life of him, whoſe conſtant buſineſs it hath been (as of all good Chriſtians) to labour for <hi>pardon,</hi> and <hi>grace;</hi> the Benefits, ſealed to Believers in that Sacrament by <hi>Him,</hi> who purchaſed them for us with his moſt precious blood; as in that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorative</hi> Sacrifice is moſt lively repreſented to us. The <hi>Inſtitution</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:38508:78"/>whereof, ſo nearly preceding the <hi>Paſſion</hi> of our Bleſſed <hi>Redeemer,</hi> doth recommend the uſe of theſe Holy Myſteries unto <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as very <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> at that time, when they are upon putting off their <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tabernacles,</hi> their corruptible Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; in expectation of a joyful <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurection,</hi> and <hi>Exaltation</hi> unto life Eternal; whereof this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, by the <hi>Primitive</hi> Fathers of the Church, eſteemed a <hi>ſure,</hi> and <hi>ſacred Pledg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A moſt comfortable <hi>Preparative</hi> whereunto (if <hi>heartily</hi> deſired, and <hi>cantiouſly</hi> and <hi>reverently</hi> admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred) is the <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>Abſolution.</hi> Which deſerves not to be the leſs eſteemed, or the more neglected, for whatſoever <hi>abuſes</hi> it hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been liable unto; when both <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> believed <hi>more</hi> of the <hi>Sacerdotal Power,</hi> than was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſo great a <hi>Truſt</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>one,</hi> and ſo ſtrict a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition</hi> required from the <hi>other;</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:38508:79"/>leſt the <hi>Minister</hi> might be <hi>Partaker of other mens ſins;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and the <hi>People</hi> delude themſelves, with <hi>unſincere</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10, 11.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:38508:79"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be uſed in a ſtate of Health.</head>
            <p>O Father of lights, from whom cometh every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift: Thou art he who tookeſt me out of my Mothers womb, and by thee have I been holden up ever ſince I was born. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of health and ſtrength, that I enjoy, are from thy goodneſs and bounty. And for them, and all thy other mercies, I bleſs and praiſe thy ever-great and glorious Name. Moſt humbly beſeeching thee to add to theſe, that bleſſing of bleſſings; the right uſe of all thy bleſſings: That through the comfort and aſſiſtance of that health, and ſtrength thou haſt given me, I may become the more diligent and faithful, in the practice of thoſe ſeveral duties of piety, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and charity, which thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt at my hands.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:38508:80"/>
            <p>And ſuffer me not, O Lord, to deceive my ſelf by a falſe account of the time of my Pilgrimage; but ſo teach me to number my days, that I may apply my heart unto wiſdom: that I may readily diſcern the vaſt difference between this ſpan of life, and the infinite ſpaces of eternity: between the pleaſures of ſin for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the everlaſting fulneſs of joy in thy preſence.</p>
            <p>And for this end, remove far away from me all thoſe vices, to which health and eaſe are apt to betray me: eſpecially all carnal ſecurity, luſt, pride, anger, want of compaſſion, misſpending my time, forgetfulneſs of thee, and of thy ways and works: And implant in my mind the daily remembrance of death, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the neceſſity of working out my ſalvation with fear and trembling; and the miſery of being ſurpriz'd by the coming of our Lord, in my ſins, or fruitleſs repentance. So that the health of my body may, through thy
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:38508:80"/>bleſſing, promote the health of my Soul; and thy augmenting the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my Talents, increaſe both my labour, and reward. That paſſing the time of my ſojourning here in fear, I may treaſure up for my ſelf ſuch ſpiritual ſtrength and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as may ſtand me in ſtead, when I ſhall lye down on my bed of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and death; adminiſtring comfort to my ſoul in the conſcience of well doing; which thou haſt promiſed us to accept and reward, through thy mercies in Jeſus Chriſt, our only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:38508:81"/>
            <head>A Prayer when one perceives himſelf to be ſick.</head>
            <p>O Lord my God, I have learn'd from thy Holy Word, and by daily experience in this vale of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that duſt I am, and unto duſt I ſhall return; that I muſt put off this earthly Tabernacle; and that thou wilt bring me to death, and the houſe appointed for all living. And now, Lord, I feel in my ſelf the uſual ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons thy good providence doth give us, to review our accounts, and to ſit our ſelves for death and judgment. Bleſſed be thy Name for this thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy! that thou haſt not taken advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of me, whil'ſt I was thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to cut me off ſuddenly in my ſins, and hurry me hence in mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but haſt given me the time, means, and I truſt, grace for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment of life. And though I have not improved (ſuch hath been my negligence and ſloth!)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:38508:81"/>theſe rich favours, to that great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage I might, and ſhould have done; yet I beſeech thee; O Lord, for thine infinite mercies in thy ſon Chriſt Jeſus, that thou wilt not be extream to mark what I have done amiſs, and to lay my ſins to my charge; but that thou wilt deal mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully with me, thy moſt unworthy ſervant, blotting out all my ſins and tranſgreſſions, that none of mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities may be mentioned unto me, in that great and terrible day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as thou alone, in whoſe hands our times are, doſt know, what will be the iſſue of this my preſent diſtemper, and ſickneſs; cauſe me to reflect on it, as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thy Will, and Wiſdom; and cheerfully and thankfully to ſubmit to this chaſtiſement, as a means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by thee, for the benefit and comfort of my Soul; and vouchſafe unto me that grace, which may ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me to receive profit thereby; and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:38508:82"/>from experience of thy goodneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, to gain hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thy love. And if thou haſt reſerv'd for me the bleſſing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring me to my former health, (which I beſeech thee to do) direct me to the uſe of ſuch means, as thou wilt make effectual for that end. But if the days of my warfare are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed; prepare me, O Lord, for a ſafe, quiet, and comfortable depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this life; and fit me for thy prefence, and glory. O Lord, ſtrengthen me againſt all the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practices, and devices of my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til, and implacable enemy; againſt all errours, and deluſions of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; the allurements of this World, inordinate love of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Life, and the terrours of Death; by filling my heart with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine comforts, by ſtrengthening my Faith in thy mercies, through Chriſt Jeſus, by repreſenting to my thoughts his victory over Death; and thoſe unconceiveable, and endleſs joys,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:38508:82"/>which thou haſt prepared for them that love thee. That neither life nor death, hight nor depth, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nor things to come, may be able to ſeparate me from the Love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus, our Lord and only Bleſſed Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:38508:83"/>
            <head>Prayers to be uſed in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord and heavenly Father, who reneweſt thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto us from day to day, making the outgoings of the Morning and Evening to praiſe thee; We give thee humble thanks for the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy loving providence over us, vouchſafed unto us in our preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation this night, and the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſt wherewith thou haſt refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our frail bodies. Humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee to pardon unto us, whatſoever ſins the ſubtilty and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Satan, or our own corrupt nature, and vain imagination have made us guilty of this night, and all the times, and days, and nights of our lives, until this preſent hour.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:38508:83"/>
               <p>And we moſt humbly beſeech thee to make this, and all other thy good mercies beſtowed upon us, ſerviceable to the advancement of thy glory, and the good of thy Church: That we may not by waſting any of thy precious Talents vouchſafed unto us, or by abuſing, and miſapplying the comforts thou giveſt us, render our ſelves accountable to thy dreadful Majeſty, as well for the good we have received, as for the evil we have committed. But let all the good things thou haſt done unto us, (vile and miſerable ſinners) increaſe a love of thy Divine Majeſty in our hearts; and perfect the practice of true holineſs, and righteouſneſs in our converſation, through the merits and interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord and only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Almighty God, by whoſe Spirit the whole body of thy Church is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned and ſanctified, receive the Supplications and Prayers, which we humbly offer to thy Divine Majeſty,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:38508:84"/>for all eſtates, and conditions of Men, in thy Holy Congregation.</p>
               <p>Particularly, for all Chriſtian Kings, Princes, and Governours; more eſpecially for thy Servant <hi>Charles,</hi> our King, That they may be preſerved from all Treachery and Violence; and that they may uſe their Power for the encouragement of them that do well, and for a terrour unto evil doers. For Subjects, that they may ſubmit unto the higher Powers for conſcience ſake, as being ordained of God. For the Nobility and Gentry, that they may give good examples, as they are great in Place. For the Clergy, that their holineſs may be according to the Shekel of the Sanctuary, and that they may be able to divide the Word of truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, giving unto every one his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in due ſeaſon. For the Rich, that they may be ready to give, and glad to diſtribute, laying up for themſelves treaſures in Heaven. For the Poor, that they may be diligent,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:38508:84"/>honeſt, and contented; and that there be never wanting thoſe, who will ſtrengthen the hands of the Poor and Needy. For the Fatherleſs and Widows, that thou wouldeſt be a Father to the one, and an Husband to the other. For the Labouring-Man, that thou wouldeſt give him an healthful body, a patient mind, and that thou wouldſt proſper unto him the work of his hands. For thoſe who are at eaſe, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> Pride, abundance of Idleneſs, and fulneſs of Bread. For the Priſoners and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that their bread may not fail, and that the hearts of their Brethren may not be hardened againſt them. For the ſick in Body, that they may cheerfully ſubmit to Gods afflicting hand, and that their patience may have its perfect work. For thoſe who are in health, that they may not remove far from them the evil day, but may ſhew themſelves wiſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering their latter end. For thoſe
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:38508:85"/>who are afflicted in mind, that thou wouldſt help them to put on the Breaſt-plate of Faith, and for an Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, the hope of Salvation, and that thou wouldſt make them to ſee thy faithfulneſs, in not permitting them to be tempted above what they are able to bear. For Parents, that they may be careful to provide for the welfare of their Childrens Souls and Bodies, bringing them up in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Lord. For Children, that they may love, honour, and reverence their Parents, obeying them in all things. For Husbands, that they may love their Wives as their own bodies, not being bitter againſt them; but giving them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as to the weaker veſſels, and being heirs together of the grace of life. For Wives, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and be in ſubjection to their Husbands, labouring to be adorned with a meek, and quiet ſpirit. For the Unmarried, that they may not ſpend their precious Talents in the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:38508:85"/>pleaſures of ſin, and vanity of life; but that they may be pure and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, attending upon the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtraction. For the Antient, that they may be ſober, grave, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, ſound in Faith, in Charity, in Patience. For the Young, that they may be ſober-minded, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing the Aged as Fathers, being ready to be taught by their wiſdom, and experience, and to follow good counſels, and examples. For Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that they may behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves prudently, juſtly, and gently towards their Servants, as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they alſo have a Maſter in Heaven. For Servants, that they may be ſubject to their Maſters with all fear, not with eye-ſervice, as men-pleaſers; but willingly, and from the heart, ſhewing all good fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity. For Teachers, that they may watch over the Souls of them who are committed to their charge, as they that muſt give an account, that they may do it with joy, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:38508:86"/>not with grief. For Learners, that they may eſteem highly of their Teachers for their works ſake, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving all opportunities of being benefited by them. For true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, that they may daily grow in grace, being ſtrengthned with might by the ſpirit in the inner man. For bare Profeſſors of Religion, that they may leave off to deny him in their works whom they profeſs with their mouths, and that they may have the power, as well as the form of godlineſs. For our Friends and Kinsfolks according to the fleſh, that being graffed together in the ſame common faith, we may together at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto the perfection of Charity in the World to come. For our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that they may not be reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, as they have dealt with us; but that we may melt them into an affection of us, by returning to them good for evil. For all that have done good unto us, that thou wouldeſt remember them, O our
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:38508:86"/>God, for their good, recompenſing them with thy Bleſſings in this life, and eternal glory in the world to come.</p>
               <p>And we moſt humbly beſeech thee, the infinitely wiſe and all-ſeeing God, that thou wilt of thy great mercy grant all thoſe things, that we have now prayed for; and all other things, which thou knoweſt to be needful both for our ſelves, and for others, and for thy whole Church; for the merits and interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, our only Mediator and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:38508:87"/>
               <head>For a Family.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Lord God, the Father of all the Families of the Earth, who art no reſpecter of Perſons, but requireſt every one to walk faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in that vocation wherein thou haſt placed him, we humbly beſeech thee for thy bleſſing on every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this Family; that each of us may perform his duty, in that inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and uprightneſs of heart, as becometh them, who profeſs the ſame Goſpel of thy ſon Chriſt Jeſus. O drive away, and keep off from hence, as all other, ſo eſpecially the ſins of this corrupt Age. Let not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Pride, Idleneſs, Hypocriſy, Unclean Luſts, Covetouſneſs, Lying, or any other ſin whatſoever, become a fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Leproſie in the walls of this Houſe. But as thou haſt given us a Bleſſing above many other our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:38508:87"/>ſo give us grace to expreſs a more ſpecial performance of duty in acknowledgment thereof. Let the hand of thy good providence be ſtretcht forth to defend us, in all dangers of Soul, and Body: give us wiſdom to diſcern, and courage to withſtand all aſſaults of the Fleſh, the World, and the Devil: Let thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly corrections of us be always an advantage to our Religious Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation: Give us thankful hearts for all thy Bleſſings: And ſo guide us in all things with thy merciful hand, that finally we may be brought to the land of everlaſting Life, there to reign with thee World without end, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:38508:88"/>
               <head>An Evening Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Moſt Powerful God and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father, to whom the light diſcovereth nothing, and from whom the Night cannot conceal us, but the darkneſs and the light to thee are both alike; leave us not, we pray thee, to the dangers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforts of this Night; but let thine eye, which ſlumbereth and ſleepeth not, watch over us for the good, both of our Souls and Bodies. O let not the darkneſs of the night, nor the privacy of our retirements betray us to do any thing unworthy of our Chriſtian calling, and that inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble light, in the preſence, and by the power of which, we live, and move, and have our being: But ſit, and prepare each of our hearts, by the inſpiration of thy Holy Spirit, to a conſtant, and ſincere obedience of thy Holy Will; that both in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:38508:88"/>and in private, we may do as becometh an holy ſeed, and a People zealous of good works; endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all things to ſhew our ſelves mindful of that ineſtimable price, which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath paid for us, vile and miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And we humbly pray thee, O Lord, to pardon, as all other, ſo the ſins and imperfections of which we have been guilty this day: That if any of us ſhall be ſummon'd from the bed of our reſt, to that of our death; we may through thy mercy, have a comfortable, and cheerful paſſage, from this life of miſery and mortality, unto a life of everlaſting happineſs, and glory; through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, and only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:89"/>
            <head>A Brief Catalogue of Books new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Printed and Reprinted for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to his Moſt Sacred Majeſty.</head>
            <p>THE works of the Reverend and Learned <hi>Henry Hammond,</hi> D. D. containing a Collection of Diſcourſes chiefly Practical, with many Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Corrections from the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s own hand; together with the Life of the <hi>Author,</hi> enlarg'd by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Fell</hi> Dean of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> In large Folio.</p>
            <p>Σ Υ'МВΟΛΟΝ ΘЕΟΛΟΓΙΚΟ'Ν.</p>
            <p>Or, a Collection of Polemical Diſcourſes addreſſed againſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> both Papiſts and Fanaticks, in large <hi>Folio,</hi> by <hi>Jeremiah Taylor,</hi> Chaplain in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of Bleſſed Memory, and late Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Down</hi> and <hi>Conner.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38508:89"/>
            <p>Animadverſions upon a Book, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> Fanatically im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and the Imputation Refuted and Retorted by <hi>S. C.</hi> The Second Edition. By a Perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Serious and compaſſionate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the Cauſes of the preſent Neglect and Contempt of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reflexions upon the <hi>Devotions</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> With the <hi>Prayers, Hymns</hi> and <hi>Leſſons</hi> themſelves, taken out of their <hi>Authentick Authors.</hi> In Three Parts. In <hi>Octavo,</hi> New.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtian Sacrifice,</hi> and the <hi>Devout Christian,</hi> and <hi>Advice to a Friend,</hi> theſe laſt three Books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Reverend <hi>S. P.</hi> D. D. in 12.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
